<title>Emil Kraepelin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10002</id>
    <revision>
      <id>623951426</id>
      <parentid>623450267</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-03T03:07:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dexbot</username>
        <id>16752040</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Removing Link GA template ([[d:Wikidata:Development plan#Badges|handled by wikidata]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox scientist
| name              = Emil Kraepelin
| image             = Emil Kraepelin 1926.jpg
| image_size        = 
| alt               = 
| caption           = Emil Kraepelin in his later years
| birth_date        = {{Birth date|df=yes|1856|02|15}} 
| birth_place       = [[Neustrelitz]]
| death_date    = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1926|10|07|1856|02|15}}
| death_place       = [[Munich]]
| resting_place     = 
| resting_place_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{Coord|LAT|LONG|type:landmark|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
| residence         = 
| citizenship       = 
| nationality       = [[German people|German]]
| fields            = [[Psychiatry]]
| workplaces        = [[University of Dorpat]],&lt;br /&gt;[[University of Heidelberg]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich|University of Munich]]

| alma_mater        = [[Leipzig University]],&lt;br /&gt;[[University of Würzburg]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich|University of Munich]]
| thesis_title      = The Place of Psychology in Psychiatry
| thesis_url        = 
| thesis_year       = 
| doctoral_advisor  = 
| academic_advisors = 
| doctoral_students = 
| notable_students  = 
| known_for         = [[Classification of mental disorders]], &lt;br /&gt;[[Kraepelinian dichotomy]]
| author_abbrev_bot = 
| author_abbrev_zoo = 
| influences        = [[Wilhelm Wundt]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Bernhard von Gudden]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Karl Ludwig Kahlbaum]]
| influenced        = [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]], &lt;br /&gt;[[International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems]]
| awards            = 
| signature         = Emil_Kraepelin_signature.JPG
| signature_alt     = 
| website           = 
| footnotes         = 
| spouse            = 
}}
'''Emil Kraepelin''' (15 February 1856 – 7 October 1926) was a [[Germany|German]] [[psychiatrist]]. [[Hans Eysenck|H.J. Eysenck]]'s ''Encyclopedia of Psychology'' identifies him as the founder of modern scientific [[psychiatry]], as well as of [[psychopharmacology]] and [[psychiatric genetics]]. Kraepelin believed the chief origin of psychiatric [[disease]] to be [[biological process|biological]] and [[Genetics|genetic]] malfunction. His theories dominated psychiatry at the start of the twentieth century and, despite the later [[psychodynamic]] influence of [[Sigmund Freud]] and his disciples, enjoyed a revival at century's end.

== Family and early life ==
Kraepelin, the son of a [[civil servant]], was born in 1856 in [[Neustrelitz]], in the [[Duchy of Mecklenburg-Strelitz]] in [[Germany]].  He was first introduced to biology by his brother Karl, 10 years older and, later, the director of the Zoological Museum of Hamburg.&lt;ref&gt;On Kraepelin's early life and family, see Burgmair et al., vol. I. as well as his ''Memoirs'' (Berlin: Springer, 1987).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
[[File:Kraepelin.JPG|thumb|Grave in Heidelberg (2008)]]
Kraepelin began his medical studies at 18, in [[University of Leipzig|Leipzig]] and [[University of Würzburg|Würzburg]], Germany.  At [[Leipzig]], he studied neuropathology under [[Paul Flechsig]] and experimental psychology with [[Wilhelm Wundt]]. Kraepelin would be a disciple of Wundt and had a lifelong interest in [[experimental psychology]] based on his theories. While there, Kraepelin wrote a prize-winning essay, &quot;The Influence of Acute Illness in the Causation of Mental Disorders.&quot;  He received his medical degree (M.D.) in 1878. In 1879, he went to work with [[Bernhard von Gudden]] at the University of Munich, where he completed his thesis, &quot;The Place of Psychology in Psychiatry&quot;. Returning to the University of Leipzig in 1882, he worked in [[Wilhelm Heinrich Erb]]'s neurology clinic and in Wundt's psychopharmacology laboratory.&lt;ref name=Alic2001&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/Emil_Kraepelin.aspx#2 Kraepelin, Emil (1856-1926)] by Margaret Alic, Gale Encyclopedia of Psychology, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

Kraepelin's major work, ''Compendium der Psychiatrie'', was first published in 1883.  In it, he argued that psychiatry was a branch of medical science and should be investigated by observation and experimentation like the other natural sciences.  He called for research into the physical causes of mental illness, and started to establish the foundations of the modern classification system for mental disorders.  Kraepelin proposed that by studying case histories and identifying specific disorders, the progression of mental illness could be predicted, after taking into account individual differences in personality and patient age at the onset of disease.&lt;ref name=Alic2001/&gt;

In 1884 he became senior physician in the Prussian provincial town of [[Leubus]] and the following year he was appointed director of the Treatment and Nursing Institute in [[Dresden]].  In 1886, at the age of 30, Kraepelin was named professor of psychiatry at the [[University of Dorpat]] (today the [[University of Tartu]]) in what is today [[Estonia]] (see Burgmair et al., Vol IV). Four years later, he became department head at the [[University of Heidelberg]], where he remained until 1904.&lt;ref name=Alic2001/&gt;  Whilst at Dorpat he became the director of the eighty-bed [[Tartu University Clinic|University Clinic]]. There he began to study and record many clinical histories in detail and &quot;was led to consider the importance of the course of the illness with regard to the classification of mental disorders.&quot;

In 1903 Kraepelin moved to Munich to take up post as Professor of Clinical Psychiatry at the [[University of Munich]].{{citation needed|date=March 2013}}

He was elected a member of the [[Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences]] in 1908.{{citation needed|date=March 2013}}

In 1912 at the request of the [[German Society of Psychiatry]], he began plans to establish a centre for research. Following a large donation from the Jewish German American [[banker]] [[James Loeb]] who had at one time been a patient, and promises of support from 'patrons of science', the [[Max Planck Institute of Psychiatry|German Institute for Psychiatric Research]] was founded in 1917 in Munich.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hup.harvard.edu/features/loeb/founder.html James Loeb] Harvard University Press&lt;/ref&gt; Initially housed in existing hospital buildings, it was maintained by further donations from Loeb and his relatives. In 1924 it came under the auspices of the [[Kaiser Wilhelm Society for the Advancement of Science]]. The German American [[Rockefeller family]]'s [[Rockefeller Foundation]] made a large donation enabling the development of a new dedicated building for the institute, along Kraepelin's guidelines, which was officially opened in 1928.&lt;ref name=Alic2001/&gt;

Kraepelin spoke out against the barbarous treatment that was prevalent in the psychiatric asylums of the time, and crusaded against alcohol, capital punishment and the imprisonment rather than treatment of the insane. He rejected psychoanalytical theories that posited innate or early sexuality as the cause of mental illness, and rejected philosophical speculation as unscientific. He focused on collecting clinical data, and was particularly interested in [[neuropathology]] (e.g. diseased tissue).&lt;ref name=Alic2001/&gt;

In the later period of his career, as a convinced champion of [[social Darwinism]], he actively promoted a policy and research agenda in [[racial hygiene]] and [[eugenics]].&lt;ref name=Engstrom2006&gt;{{cite journal|author=Engstrom EJ, Weber MM, Burgmair W|title=Emil Wilhelm Magnus Georg Kraepelin (1856-1926)|url=http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?articleid=97097|journal=[[The American Journal of Psychiatry]]|date=October 2006|volume=163|issue=10|pages=1710|doi=10.1176/appi.ajp.163.10.1710|pmid=17012678}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kraepelin retired from teaching at the age of 66, spending his remaining years establishing the Institute. The final edition of his Textbook of Psychiatry was published in 1927, shortly after his death. It comprised four volumes and was ten times larger than the first edition of 1883.&lt;ref name=Alic2001/&gt;

== Theories and classification schemes ==
Kraepelin announced that he had found a new way of looking at mental illness, referring to the traditional view as &quot;symptomatic&quot; and to his view as &quot;clinical&quot;.  This turned out to be his paradigm-setting synthesis of the hundreds of mental disorders classified by the 19th century, grouping diseases together based on classification of [[syndrome]] — common ''patterns'' of symptoms over time — rather than by simple similarity of major symptoms in the manner of his predecessors. Kraepelin described his work in the 5th edition of his textbook as a &quot;decisive step from a symptomatic to a clinical view of insanity....The importance of external clinical signs has...been subordinated to consideration of the conditions of origin, the course, and the
terminus which result from individual disorders. Thus, all purely symptomatic categories have disappeared from the nosology.&quot;&lt;ref name=decker/&gt;

=== Psychosis and mood ===
Kraepelin is specifically credited with the classification of what was previously considered to be a [[Unitary psychosis|unitary concept of psychosis]], into two distinct forms (known as the [[Kraepelinian dichotomy]]):

* [[Bipolar disorder|manic depression]] (now seen as comprising a range of mood disorders such as [[clinical depression|recurrent major depression]] and [[bipolar disorder]]), and
* [[dementia praecox]].

Drawing on his long-term research, and using the criteria of course, outcome and prognosis, he developed the concept of [[dementia praecox]], which he defined as the &quot;sub-acute development of a peculiar simple condition of mental weakness occurring at a youthful age.&quot;  When he first introduced this concept as a diagnostic entity in the fourth German edition of his ''Lehrbuch der Psychiatrie'' in 1893, it was placed among the degenerative disorders alongside, but separate from, [[catatonia]] and [[dementia paranoides]]. At that time, the concept corresponded by and large with [[Ewald Hecker]]'s [[hebephrenia]]. In the sixth edition of the ''Lehrbuch'' in 1899 all three of these clinical types are treated as different expressions of one disease, dementia praecox.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Yuhas|first=Daisy|title=Throughout History, Defining Schizophrenia Has Remained a Challenge (Timeline)|url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=throughout-history-defining-schizophrenia-has-remained-challenge|publisher=Scientific American Mind (March 2013)|accessdate=2 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the cardinal principles of his method was the recognition that any given symptom may appear in virtually any one of these disorders; e.g., there is almost no single symptom occurring in dementia praecox which cannot sometimes be found in manic-depression. What distinguishes each disease symptomatically (as opposed to the underlying pathology) is not any particular (pathognomonic) symptom or symptoms, but a specific pattern of symptoms. In the absence of a direct physiological or genetic test or marker for each disease, it is only possible to distinguish them by their specific pattern of symptoms. Thus, Kraepelin's system is a method for pattern recognition, not grouping by common symptoms.

Kraepelin also demonstrated specific patterns in the genetics of these disorders and specific and characteristic patterns in their course and outcome.{{citation needed|date=March 2013}} Generally speaking, there tend to be more schizophrenics among the relatives of schizophrenic patients than in the general population, while manic-depression is more frequent in the relatives of manic-depressives. Though, of course, this does not demonstrate genetic linkage, as this might be a socio-environmental factor as well.{{citation needed|date=March 2013}}

He also reported a pattern to the course and outcome of these conditions. Kraepelin believed that schizophrenia had a deteriorating course in which mental function continuously (although perhaps erratically) declines, while manic-depressive patients experienced a course of illness which was intermittent, where patients were relatively symptom-free during the intervals which separate acute episodes. This led Kraepelin to name what we now know as schizophrenia, dementia praecox (the [[dementia]] part signifying the irreversible mental decline). It later became clear that dementia praecox did not necessarily lead to mental decline and was thus renamed [[schizophrenia]] by [[Eugen Bleuler]] to correct Kraepelin's misnomer.

In addition, as Kraepelin accepted in 1920, &quot;It is becoming increasingly obvious that we cannot satisfactorily distinguish these two diseases&quot;; however, he maintained that &quot;On the one hand we find those patients with irreversible dementia and severe cortical lesions. On the other are those patients whose personality remains intact.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Berrios, GE., Luque, R., Villagran, JM. (2003). [http://www.ijpsy.com/volumen3/num2/60/schizophrenia-a-conceptual-history-esquizofrenia-EN.pdf Schizophrenia: a conceptual history]. International Journal of Psychology and Psychological Therapy 3: No 2: 111–140&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, overlap between the diagnoses and neurological abnormalities (when found) have continued, and in fact a diagnostic category of [[schizoaffective disorder]] would be brought in to cover the intermediate cases.

Kraepelin devoted very few pages to his speculations about the etiology of his two major insanities, dementia praecox and manic-depressive insanity. However, from 1896 to his death in 1926 he held to the speculation that these insanities (particularly dementia praecox) would one day probably be found to be caused by a gradual systemic or &quot;whole body&quot; disease process, probably metabolic, which affected many of the organs and nerves in the body but affected the brain in a final, decisive cascade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Noll|first=Richard|title=Whole Body Madness|url=http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/display/article/10168/2104852|publisher=Psychiatric Times|accessdate=26 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Psychopathic personalities ===
In the first through sixth edition of Kraepelin's influential psychiatry textbook, there was a section on [[moral insanity]], which meant then a disorder of the emotions or moral sense without apparent delusions or hallucinations, and which Kraepelin defined as 'lack or weakness of those sentiments which counter the ruthless satisfaction of egotism'. He attributed this mainly to degeneration. This has been described as a psychiatric redefinition of [[Cesare Lombroso]]'s theories of the 'born criminal', conceptualised as a '[[moral]] defect', though Kraepelin stressed it was not yet possible to recognise them by physical characteristics.&lt;ref name=Wetzell2000&gt;Richard F. Wetzell (2000) [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=iGW7QLJmuwoC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Inventing the criminal: a history of German criminology, 1880-1945] from pg 59 &amp; from 146, misc&lt;/ref&gt;

In fact from 1904 Kraepelin changed the section heading to 'The born criminal', moving it from under 'Congenital feeblemindedness' to a new chapter on 'Psychopathic personalities'. They were treated under a theory of degeneration. Four types were distinguished: born criminals (inborn delinquents), [[pathological liars]], [[querulous]] persons, and Triebmenschen (persons driven by a basic compulsion, including [[Vagabond (person)|vagabonds]], [[spendthrifts]], and [[dipsomaniacs]]). The concept of '[[psychopathic]] inferiorities' had been recently popularised in Germany by [[Julius Ludwig August Koch]], who proposed congenital and acquired types. Kraepelin had no evidence or explanation suggesting a congenital cause, and his assumption therefore appears to have been simple '[[biologism]]'. Others, such as [[Gustav Aschaffenburg]], argued for a varying combination of causes. Kraepelin's assumption of a moral defect rather than a positive drive towards crime has also been questioned, as it implies that the moral sense is somehow inborn and unvarying, yet it was known to vary by time and place, and Kraepelin never considered that the moral sense might just be different. [[Kurt Schneider]] criticized Kraepelin's nosology for appearing to be a list of behaviors that he considered undesirable, rather than medical conditions, though Schneider's alternative version has also been criticised on the same basis. Nevertheless, many essentials of these diagnostic systems were introduced into the diagnostic systems, and remarkable similarities remain in the DSM-IV and ICD-10.&lt;ref name=Wetzell2000/&gt; The issues would today mainly be considered under the category of [[personality disorders]], or in terms of Kraepelin's focus on [[psychopathy]].

Kraepelin had referred to psychopathic conditions (or 'states') in his 1896 edition, including compulsive insanity, impulsive insanity, [[homosexuality]], and mood disturbances. From 1904, however, he instead termed those 'original disease conditions', and introduced the new alternative category of psychopathic personalities. In the eighth edition from 1909 that category would include, in addition to a separate 'dissocial' type, the excitable, the unstable, the Triebmenschen driven persons, eccentrics, the liars and swindlers, and the quarrelsome. It has been described as remarkable that Kraepelin now considered mood disturbances to be not part of the same category, but only attenuated (more mild) phases of manic depressive illness; this corresponds to current classification schemes.&lt;ref&gt;Henning Sass &amp; Alan Felthous (2008) Chapter 1: History and Conceptual Development of Psychopathic Disorders in [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=8WhcGo-1MkYC&amp;dq=kurt+schneider+psychopaths&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s International Handbook on Psychopathic Disorders and the Law]. Edited by Alan Felthous, Henning Sass&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Alzheimer's disease ===
Kraepelin postulated that there is a specific brain or other biological pathology underlying each of the major psychiatric disorders.{{citation needed|date=March 2013}} As a colleague of [[Alois Alzheimer]], and co-discoverer of [[Alzheimer's disease]], it was his laboratory which discovered its pathologic basis. Kraepelin was confident that it would someday be possible to identify the pathologic basis of each of the major psychiatric disorders.{{citation needed|date=March 2013}}

=== Degeneration of the race ===
Upon moving to become Professor of Clinical Psychiatry at the [[University of Munich]] in 1903, Kraepelin increasingly wrote on social policy issues. He was a strong and influential proponent of [[eugenics]] and [[racial hygiene]]. His publications included a focus on [[alcoholism]], [[crime]], [[degeneration]] and [[hysteria]].&lt;ref name=Engstrom2007&gt;{{cite journal|last=Engstrom|first=E. J.|title=On the Question of Degeneration' by Emil Kraepelin (1908)1|journal=[[History of Psychiatry (journal)|History of Psychiatry]]|date=1 September 2007|volume=18|issue=3|pages=389–398|doi=10.1177/0957154X07079689|pmid=18175639|url=http://134.76.163.171:8080/jspui/bitstream/123456789/10898/1/PEER_stage2_10.1177%252F0957154X07079689.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kraepelin was convinced that such institutions as the [[education system]] and the [[welfare state]], because of their trend to break the processes of [[natural selection]], undermined the Germans’ biological &quot;struggle for survival.&quot;&lt;ref name=Engstrom2006/&gt; He was concerned to preserve and enhance the German people, the [[Volk]], in the sense of nation or race. He appears to have held [[Lamarckian]] concepts of evolution, such that cultural deterioration could be inherited. He was a strong ally and promoter of the work of fellow psychiatrist [[Ernst Rudin]] to clarify the mechanisms of genetic inheritance as to make a so-called '[[empirical]] genetic [[prognosis]]'.&lt;ref name=Engstrom2007/&gt;

Martin Brune has pointed out that Kraepelin and Rudin also appear to have been ardent advocates of a [[self-domestication]] theory, a version of [[social darwinism]] which held that modern culture was not allowing people to be weeded out, resulting in more mental disorder and deterioration of the gene pool. Kraepelin saw a number of 'symptoms' of this, such as &quot;weakening of viability and resistance, decreasing fertility, proletarianisation, and moral damage due to 'penning up people' [original 'Zusammenpferchung']&quot;. He also wrote that &quot;the number of idiots, epileptics, psychopaths, criminals, prostitutes, and tramps who descend from alcoholic and syphilitic parents, and who transfer their inferiority to their offspring, is incalculable.&quot; He felt that &quot;the well-known example of the [[Jews]], with their strong disposition towards nervous and mental disorders, teaches us that their extraordinarily advanced domestication may eventually imprint clear marks on the race&quot;. Brune states that Kraepelin's [[nosological]] system was 'to a great deal, built on the degeneration [[paradigm]]'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Brüne|first=Martin|title=On human self-domestication, psychiatry, and eugenics|journal=Philosophy, Ethics, and Humanities in Medicine|date=1 January 2007|volume=2|issue=1|pages=21|doi=10.1186/1747-5341-2-21|pmid=17919321|pmc=2082022|url=http://www.peh-med.com/content/2/1/21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Influence ==
Kraepelin's great contribution in classifying schizophrenia and manic-depression remains relatively unknown to the general public, and his work, which had neither the literary quality nor paradigmatic power of Freud's, is little read outside scholarly circles. Kraepelin's contributions were also to a large extent marginalized throughout a good part of the twentieth century during the success of Freudian etiological theories. However, his views now dominate many quarters of psychiatric research and academic psychiatry. His fundamental theories on the diagnosis of psychiatric disorders form the basis of the major diagnostic systems in use today, especially the [[American Psychiatric Association]]'s [[DSM-IV]] and the [[World Health Organization]]'s [[ICD]] system, based on the [[Research Diagnostic Criteria]] and earlier [[Feighner Criteria]] developed by espoused 'neo-kraepelinians', though [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] and others in the DSM committees were keen not to include assumptions about causation as Kraepelin had.&lt;ref name=decker&gt;[http://peer.ccsd.cnrs.fr/docs/00/57/08/96/PDF/PEER_stage2_10.1177%252F0957154X07078976.pdf Hannah S Decker, How Kraepelinian was Kraepelin? How Kraepelinian are the neo-Kraepelinians? - from Emil Kraepelin to DSM-III] Special Edition of History of Psychiatry, 18(3): 337–360 {{DOI|10.1177/0957154X07078976}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Eric J. Engstrom and Matthias Weber. [http://www.tara.tcd.ie/bitstream/2262/51636/1/PEER_stage2_10.1177%252F0957154X07080819.pdf Making Kraepelin History: A Great Instauration?]: Special Issue of History of Psychiatry 18.3 (2007): 267-273.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kraepelin has been described as a 'scientific manager' and political operator, who developed a large-scale, clinically oriented, epidemiological research programme. In this role he took in clinical information from a wide range of sources and networks. Despite proclaiming high clinical standards for himself to gather information 'by means of expert analysis of individual cases', he would also draw on the reported observations of officials not trained in psychiatry. The various editions of his textbooks do not contain detailed case histories of individuals, however, but mosaic-like compilations of typical statements and behaviors from patients with a specific diagnosis. In broader terms, he has been described as a [[bourgeois]] or [[reactionary]] citizen.&lt;ref name=Engstrom2007/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Shepherd|first=M.|title=Two faces of Emil Kraepelin|journal=[[The British Journal of Psychiatry]]|date=1 August 1995|volume=167|issue=2|pages=174–183|doi=10.1192/bjp.167.2.174|pmid=7582666}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kraepelin wrote in a ''knapp und klar'' (concise and clear) style that made his books useful tools for physicians. Abridged and clumsy English translations of the sixth and seventh editions of his textbook in 1902 and 1907 (respectively) by Allan Ross Diefendorf (1871-1943), an assistant physician at the Connecticut Hospital for the Insane at Middletown, inadequately conveyed the literary quality of his writings that made them so valuable to practitioners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Noll|first=Richard|title=The Bed Makes Gestures|url=http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/blog/psych-history/content/article/10168/2125478|publisher=Psychiatric times|accessdate=February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Dreams ==
In the Heidelberg and early Munich years he edited ''Psychologische Arbeiten'', a journal on experimental psychology. One of his own famous contributions to this journal also appeared in the form of a monograph (105 p.) entitled ''Über Sprachstörungen im Traume''  (on language disturbances in dreams).&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=8RxWAAAAMAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage&amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;cad=0 Über Sprachstörungen im Traume] (1906)&lt;/ref&gt; Kraepelin, on the basis on the dream-[[psychosis]] analogy, studied for more than 20 years [[dream speech|language disorder in dreams]] in order to study indirectly [[schizophasia]]. The dreams Kraepelin collected are mainly his own. They lack extensive comment by the dreamer. In order to study them the full range of biographical knowledge available today on Kraepelin is necessary (see e.g. Burgmair et al., I-VII).

== Bibliography ==
*Kraepelin, E. (1906). ''Über Sprachstörungen im Traume''. Leizpig: Engelmann.[http://books.google.com/books?id=8RxWAAAAMAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage&amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;cad=0]
*Kraepelin, E. (1987). ''Memoirs.'' Berlin, Heidelberg, New York: Springer-Verlag. ISBN 978-3-642-71926-4

== Notes ==
&lt;references/&gt;

== References ==
*Burgmair, Wolfgang &amp; Eric J. Engstrom &amp; Matthias Weber, et al., eds. ''Emil Kraepelin''. 7 vols. Munich: belleville, 2000-2008.
**Vol. VII: Kraepelin in Munich, Teil II: 1914-1920 (2009), ISBN 978-3-933510-96-9
**Vol. VI: Kraepelin in Munich, Teil I: 1903-1914 (2006), ISBN 3-933510-95-3
**Vol. V: Kraepelin in Heidelberg, 1891-1903 (2005), ISBN 3-933510-94-5
**Vol. IV: Kraepelin in Dorpat, 1886-1891 (2003), ISBN 3-933510-93-7
**Vol. III: Briefe I, 1868-1886 (2002), ISBN 3-933510-92-9
**Vol. II: Kriminologische und forensische Schriften: Werke und Briefe (2001), ISBN 3-933510-91-0
**Vol. I: Persönliches, Selbstzeugnisse (2000), ISBN 3-933510-90-2
*Noll, Richard (2011) ''American Madness: The Rise and Fall of Dementia Praecox.'' Cambridge and London: Harvard University Press.
*Briole, G. (2012). &quot;Emil Kraepelin: The Fragility of a Colossal Oeuvre&quot;. ''Hurly-Burly'' '''8''': 125-147.

== External links ==
*[http://www.kraepelin.org/_wsn/page3.html Extensive bibliography of English translations of Kraepelin's works]
*[http://www.mpipsykl.mpg.de/ Extensive bibliography of works by and about Kraepelin's including those in the original German]
*[http://www.kraepelin.org/ International Kraepelin Society contact]
*[https://archive.org/details/bersprachstrung00kraegoog Kraepelin's monograph ''Über Sprachstörungen im Traume'']
*[http://www.pulse-project.org/node/150 Pulse-Project Audio Lecture: Dr. Octavian Buda on &quot;From Psychiatry in Dorpat to Eugenics in Munich: The late works of Emil Kraepelin.&quot;]
For biographies of Kraepelin see:
* [http://www.engstrom.de/KRAEPELINBIOGRAPHY.pdf engstrom.de/KRAEPELINBIOGRAPHY.pdf]
* [http://www.uni-leipzig.de/~psy/eng/kraep-e.html uni-leipzig.de/~psy/eng/kraep-e.html] and
* [http://websrv.ucsu.edu/facstaff/tbrown/times/obits/kraepelin.htm ebsrv.ucsu.edu/facstaff/tbrown/times/obits/kraepelin.htm]
For English translations of Kraepelin's work see:
*[http://hpy.sagepub.com/content/21/3/340.full.pdf+html On Uprootedness (1921)]
*[http://hpy.sagepub.com/content/13/49/98.full.pdf+html Emil Kraepelin's Clinical Self-Assessment (1920)]
*[http://hpy.sagepub.com/content/3/10/256.full.pdf+html Psychiatric Observations on Contemporary Issues (1919)]
*[http://hpy.sagepub.com/content/18/3/399.full.pdf+html On the Question of Degeneration (1908)]
*[http://hpy.sagepub.com/content/16/3/350.full.pdf+html The Directions of Psychiatric Research (1887)]

{{Bipolar disorder}}

{{Authority control|VIAF=44300913}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Kraepelin, Emil
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = German psychiatrist
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 15 February 1856
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Neustrelitz]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = 7 October 1926
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Munich]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Kraepelin, Emil}}
[[Category:1856 births]]
[[Category:1926 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Neustrelitz]]
[[Category:German psychiatrists]]
[[Category:German neuroscientists]]
[[Category:University of Tartu faculty]]
[[Category:German Fatherland Party politicians]]
[[Category:Psychosis]]
[[Category:People from Mecklenburg-Strelitz]]
[[Category:Members of the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences]]
[[Category:Bipolar disorder researchers]]
[[Category:Leipzig University alumni]]
[[Category:History of psychiatry]]
[[Category:Psychiatry academics]]</text>
      <sha1>5plvqcht0vhl69lbvptbrvaimdtpnw3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>
    <title>Eugene Wigner</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10101</id>
    <revision>
      <id>622281450</id>
      <parentid>617992127</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-22T02:20:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DadaNeem</username>
        <id>2715142</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early life */ 3 wikilinks</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{eastern name order|Wigner Jenő}}
{{Infobox scientist
|name           = Eugene Wigner
|image             = Wigner.jpg
|image_size        = 200px
|birth_name        = Eugene Paul Wigner 
|birth_date        = {{Birth date|1902|11|17|mf=y}}
|birth_place       = [[Budapest]], [[Austria-Hungary]]
|death_date        = {{death date and age|mf=yes|1995|1|1|1902|11|17}}
|death_place       = [[Princeton, New Jersey]],&lt;br/&gt; [[United States]]
|residence         = [[United States]]
|citizenship       = [[United States|American]] (post-1937)&lt;br/&gt;[[Hungary|Hungarian]] (pre-1937)
|nationality       = 
|ethnicity         = [[Hungarian Jewish]]
|fields            = [[Theoretical Physics]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Atomic Physics]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Nuclear Physics]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Solid State Physics]]
|workplaces        = [[University of Göttingen]]&lt;br/&gt;[[University of Wisconsin–Madison]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Princeton University]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Manhattan project]]
|alma_mater        = [[Technical University of Berlin|Technische Hochschule Berlin]]
|doctoral_advisor  = [[Michael Polanyi]]
|academic_advisors = [[László Rátz]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Richard Becker]]
|doctoral_students = [[John Bardeen]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Victor Frederick Weisskopf]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Marcos Moshinsky]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Abner Shimony]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Edwin Thompson Jaynes]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Frederick Seitz]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Conyers Herring]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Fred Tappert|Frederick Tappert]]&lt;br/&gt;Francis Narcowich&lt;br/&gt;John Walter Clark&lt;br/&gt;[[Joseph O. Hirschfelder|J O Hirschfelder]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Conyers Herring]]
|notable_students  = 
|known_for         = [[Bargmann–Wigner equations]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Conservation law (physics)|Law of conservation of]] [[parity (physics)|parity]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner D-matrix]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner–Eckart theorem]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner's friend]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner semicircle distribution]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner's classification]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Wigner distribution function]]&lt;br/&gt;{{nowrap|[[Wigner quasi-probability distribution]]}}&lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner crystal]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner effect]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner energy]]  &lt;br/&gt; [[Wigner lattice]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Relativistic Breit–Wigner distribution]]  &lt;br/&gt;{{nowrap|[[Modified Wigner distribution function]]}}&lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner–d'Espagnat inequality]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[Gabor–Wigner transform]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner's theorem]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner semicircle distribution|Wigner distribution]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[Jordan–Wigner transformation]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Newton–Wigner localization]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner-Inonu contraction]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner–Seitz cell]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner–Seitz radius]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Thomas-Wigner rotation]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[Wigner–Weyl transform]]  &lt;br/&gt; [[Wigner-Wilkins Spectra]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[6-j symbol]]  &lt;br/&gt;[[9-j symbol]]
|author_abbrev_bot = 
|author_abbrev_zoo = 
|influences        = 
|influenced        = [[Erdal İnönü]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Eugene Feenberg]]&lt;br/&gt;[[George Cowan]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Robert Serber]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Igal Talmi]]
|awards            = [[Enrico Fermi Award]] (1958)&lt;br/&gt;[[Atoms for Peace Award]] (1959)&lt;br&gt;[[Max Planck Medal]] (1961)&lt;br/&gt;[[Nobel Prize in Physics]] (1963)&lt;br/&gt;[[National Medal of Science]] (1969)
|signature         = eugene_wigner_sig.jpg
|footnotes         = 
|spouse=Amelia Frank (1936–1937; her death)&lt;br/&gt;Mary Annette Wheeler (1941–1977; her death; 2 children)&lt;br/&gt;Eileen Clare-Patton Hamilton (1 child) (died November 21, 2010)
}}
'''Eugene Paul''' &quot;'''E. P.'''&quot; '''Wigner''' ({{lang-hu|Wigner Jenő Pál}}; November 17, 1902 – January 1, 1995), was a [[Hungary|Hungarian]] [[United States|American]] [[theoretical physicist]] and [[mathematician]]. He received a share of the [[Nobel Prize in Physics]] in 1963 &quot;for his contributions to the theory of the [[atomic nucleus]] and the [[elementary particles]], particularly through the discovery and application of fundamental symmetry principles&quot;; the other half of the award was shared between [[Maria Goeppert-Mayer]] and [[J. Hans D. Jensen]]. Wigner is notable for having laid the foundation for the theory of [[symmetry in physics|symmetries]] in [[quantum mechanics]]&lt;ref&gt;Wightman, A.S. (1995) ''[http://www.ams.org/notices/199507/wigner.pdf Eugene Paul Wigner 1902–1995]'', [[Notices of the American Mathematical Society|NAMS]] '''42'''(7), 769–771.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as for his research into the structure of the [[atomic nucleus]]. It was Eugene Wigner who first identified [[Xe-135]] &quot;poisoning&quot; in nuclear reactors, and for this reason it is sometimes referred to as ''Wigner poisoning''. Wigner is also important for his work in pure mathematics, having authored a number of [[mathematical theorem|theorem]]s. In particular, [[Wigner's theorem]] is a cornerstone in the [[mathematical formulation of quantum mechanics]].

==Early life==
[[File:Heisenberg,W. Wigner,E. 1928.jpg|thumb|left|[[Werner Heisenberg]] and Eugene Wigner (1928)]]
Wigner Jenő Pál was born in [[Budapest]], [[Austria-Hungary]] on November 17, 1902, to middle class [[Jewish]] parents, Elisabeth (Einhorn) and Anthony Wigner, a leather tanner. He had an older sister, Bertha, known as Biri, and a younger sister Margit, known as Manci,{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=9–12}} who later married British theoretical physicist [[Paul Dirac]].{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=164–166}} He was home schooled by a professional teacher until the age of 9, when he started school at the third grade. During this period, Wigner developed an interest in mathematical problems.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=14–15}} At the age of 11, Wigner contracted what his doctors believed to be [[tuberculosis]]. His parents sent him to live for six weeks in a [[sanatorium]] in the [[Austria]]n mountains, before the doctors concluded that the diagnosis was mistaken.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=22–24}}

Wigner's family was Jewish, but not religiously observant, and his [[Bar Mitzvah]] was a secular one. From 1915 through 1919, he studied at the [[Fasori Gimnázium|Fasori Evangélikus Gimnázium]], the school his father had attended. Religious education was compulsory, and he attended classes in [[Judaism]] taught by a rabbi.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=33–34, 47}} A fellow student was [[János von Neumann]], who was a year behind Wigner. They both benefited from the instruction of the noted [[mathematics]] teacher [[László Rátz]].{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=49–53}} In 1919, to escape the [[Béla Kun]] [[Communism|communist]] regime, the Wigner family briefly fled to Austria, returning to [[Hungary]] after Kun's downfall.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=40–43}} Partly as a reaction to the prominence of Jews in the Kun regime, the family converted to [[Lutheranism]].{{sfn|Szanton|1992|p=38}} Wigner explained later in his life that his family decision to convert to Lutheranism &quot;was not at heart a religious decision but an anti-communist one&quot;.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|p=38}} On religious views, Wigner was an atheist.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=60–61|quote=Neither did I want to be a clergyman. I liked a good sermon. But religion tells people how to behave and that I could never do. Clergymen also had to assume and advocate the presence of God, and proofs of God's existence seemed to me quite unsatisfactory. People claimed that He had made our earth. Well, how had He made it? With an earth-making machine? Someone once asked [[Saint Augustine]], &quot;What did the Lord do before he created the world?&quot; And Saint Augustine is said to have answered, &quot;He created Hell for people who ask such questions.&quot; A retort perhaps made in jest, but I knew of none better. I saw that I could not know anything of God directly, that His presence was a matter of belief, I did not have that belief, and preaching without belief is repulsive. So I could not be a clergyman, however many people might gain salvation. And my parents never pressed the point.}}

After graduating from the gimnázium in 1920, Wigner enrolled at the [[Budapest University of Technology and Economics|Budapest University of Technical Sciences]], known as the ''Műegyetem''. He was not happy with the courses on offer,{{sfn|Szanton|1992|p=59}}  and  in 1921 enrolled at the [[Technische Hochschule]] in Berlin (today the [[Technische Universität Berlin]]), where he studied [[chemical engineering]].{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=64–65}}  He also attended the Wednesday afternoon colloquia of the [[German Physical Society]]. These colloquia featured such luminaries as [[Max Planck]], [[Max von Laue]], [[Rudolf Ladenburg]], [[Werner Heisenberg]], [[Walther Nernst]], [[Wolfgang Pauli]], and [[Albert Einstein]].{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=68–75}} Wigner also met the physicist [[Leó Szilárd]], who at once became Wigner's closest friend.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=93–94}} A third experience in Berlin was formative. Wigner worked at the [[Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Physical Chemistry and Elektrochemistry]] (now the [[Fritz Haber Institute]]), and there he met [[Michael Polanyi]], who became, after László Rátz, Wigner's greatest teacher. Polanyi supervised Wigner's [[DSc]] thesis, ''Bildung und Zerfall von Molekülen'' (&quot;Formation and Decay of Molecules&quot;).{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=76–84}}

==Middle years==
Wigner returned to Budapest, where he went to work at his father's tannery, but in 1926, he accepted an offer from [[Karl Weissenberg]] at the [[Max Planck Institute for Physics|Kaiser Wilhelm Institute]] in Berlin. Weissenberg wanted someone to assist him with his work on [[x-ray]] [[crystallography]], and Polanyi had recommended Wigner. After six months as Weissenberg's assistant, Wigner went to work for [[Richard Becker]] for two semesters. Wigner explored [[quantum mechanics]], studying the work of [[Erwin Schrödinger]]. He also delved into the [[group theory]] of [[Ferdinand Georg Frobenius|Ferdinand Frobenius]] and  [[Eduard Ritter von Weber]].{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=101–106}}

Wigner received a request from [[Arnold Sommerfeld]] to work in [[Göttingen]] as an assistant to the great mathematician [[David Hilbert]]. This proved a disappointment, as Hilbert's interests had shifted to logic. Wigner nonetheless studied independently.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=109–112}}  He laid the foundation for the theory of symmetries in quantum mechanics and in 1927 introduced what is now known as the [[Wigner D-matrix]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Wigner |first=E. |year=1927 |title={{lang|de|Einige Folgerungen aus der Schrödingerschen Theorie für die Termstrukturen}} |journal=[[Zeitschrift für Physik]] |volume=43 |issue=9–10 |pages=624–652 |doi=10.1007/BF01397327 |bibcode = 1927ZPhy...43..624W }}&lt;/ref&gt; Wigner and [[Hermann Weyl]] were responsible for introducing group theory into quantum mechanics. The latter had written a standard text, ''Group Theory and Quantum Mechanics'' (1928), but it was not easy to understand, especially for younger physicists. Wigner's ''Group Theory and Its Application to the Quantum Mechanics of Atomic Spectra'' (1931) made group theory accessible to a wider audience.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=116–119}}

In the late 1930s, Wigner extended his research into atomic nuclei. He developed an important general theory of nuclear reactions, the Wigner–Eisenbud R-matrix theory, published in 1947.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/nuclear-engineering/22-106-neutron-interactions-and-applications-spring-2010/lecture-notes/MIT22_106S10_lec04b.pdf |title=Brief Review of R-Matrix Theory |first=L. C. |last=Leal |accessdate=August 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1929, his papers were drawing notice in the world of physics. In 1930, [[Princeton University]] recruited Wigner for a one-year lectureship, at 7 times the salary that he had been drawing in Europe. Princeton recruited von Neumann at the same time. Wigner and von Neumann had collaborated on three papers together in 1928 and two in 1929. They anglicized their first names to &quot;Eugene&quot; and &quot;John&quot;, respectively.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=127–132}} When their year was up, Princeton offered a five-year contract as visiting professors for half the year. The  Technische Hochschule responded with a teaching assignment for the other half of the year. This was very timely, since the [[Nazi]]s soon rose to power in Germany.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=136, 153–155}} At Princeton in 1934, Wigner introduced his sister Manci to the physicist [[Paul Dirac]], whom she married.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=163–166}}

Princeton did not rehire Wigner when his contract ran out in 1936.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=171–172}} Through [[Gregory Breit]], Wigner found new employment at the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison|University of Wisconsin]]. There he met his first wife, Amelia Frank, who was a physics student there. However she died unexpectedly in 1937, leaving Wigner distraught. He therefore accepted a 1938 offer from Princeton to return there.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=173–178}} Wigner became a [[naturalized citizen]] of the United States on January 8, 1937, and he brought his parents to the United States.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=184–185}}

==Manhattan Project==
Although he was a professed political amateur, on August 2, 1939, he introduced [[Leó Szilárd]] to [[Albert Einstein]] for a meeting that resulted in the [[Einstein-Szilárd letter]] which urged President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] to initiate the [[Manhattan Project]] to develop [[atomic bombs]].{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=197–202}} Wigner remained fearful of the Germans acquiring an atomic bomb after the war began, and even refused to have his fingerprints taken because he feared they would be used to track him down if Germany won.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|p=215}} &quot;Thoughts of being murdered,&quot; he later recalled, &quot;focus your mind wonderfully.&quot;{{sfn|Szanton|1992|p=215}}

On June 4, 1941, Wigner married his second wife, Mary Annette Wheeler, a professor of physics at [[Vassar College]], who had completed her Ph.D. at [[Yale University]] in 1932.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=205–207}} They remained married until her death in 1977.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Obituary: Mary Wigner|journal=Physics Today|date=July 1978|volume=31|issue=7|pages=58|url=http://www.physicstoday.org/resource/1/phtoad/v31/i7/p58_s2?bypassSSO=1|doi=10.1063/1.2995119|bibcode = 1978PhT....31g..58. }}&lt;/ref&gt; They had two children, David and Martha.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-history.mcs.st-andrews.ac.uk/Biographies/Wigner.html |title=Wigner Biography |accessdate=August 10, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Manhattan Project, Wigner led a team that included [[Alvin Weinberg]], Gale Young and Edward Creutz. The group's task was to design the production nuclear reactors that would convert uranium into weapons grade plutonium.  At the time, reactors existed only on paper, and no reactor had yet gone critical. In July 1942, Wigner chose a conservative 100 MW design, with a [[graphite]] [[neutron moderator]] and water cooling.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=217–218}} Wigner was present at a converted rackets court under the stands at the [[University of Chicago]]'s abandoned [[Stagg Field]] on December 2, 1942, when the world's first atomic reactor, [[Chicago Pile-1|Chicago Pile One (CP-1)]] achieved a [[nuclear chain reaction]] (a [[critical reaction]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.anl.gov/Science_and_Technology/History/cp1list.html |title=Chicago Pile 1 Pioneers |publisher=[[Los Alamos National Laboratory]] |accessdate=August 10, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wigner was disappointed that [[DuPont]] was given responsibility for the detailed design of the reactors, not just their construction. He threatened to resign in February 1943, but was talked out of it by the head of the [[Metallurgical Laboratory]],  [[Arthur Compton]], who sent him on vacation instead. As it turned out, a design decision by DuPont to give the reactor additional load tubes for more uranium saved the project when [[neutron poisoning]] became a problem. During the 1950s, he would even work for DuPont on the [[Savannah River Site]].{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=233–235}} Wigner did not regret working on the Manhattan Project, and sometimes wished the atomic bomb had been ready a year earlier.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|p=249}}

==Later years==
In 1946, Wigner accepted a position as the Director of Research at the Clinton Laboratory (now the [[Oak Ridge National Laboratory]]) in [[Oak Ridge, Tennessee]]. When the newly created Atomic Energy Commission took charge of the laboratory's operations at the start of 1947, Wigner feared that many of the technical decisions would be made in Washington.&lt;ref name=&quot;NAS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Seitz|first=Frederick|authorlink=Frederick Seitz |first2=Erich |authorlink2=Erich Vogt |last2=Vogt |first3=Alvin M. |last3=Weinberg |authorlink3=Alvin Weinberg |series=Biographical Memoirs |title=Eugene Paul Wigner |url=http://www.nap.edu/readingroom/books/biomems/ewigner.html|publisher=National Academies Press|accessdate=20 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also saw the Army's continuation of wartime security policies at the laboratory as a &quot;meddlesome oversight&quot;, interfering with research.&lt;ref name=ORNL-History-RnR&gt;{{cite web|title=ORNL History. Chapter 2: High-Flux Years. Section: Research and Regulations|url=http://web.ornl.gov/info/ornlreview/rev25-34/chapter2.shtml|work=ORNL Review|publisher=Oak Ridge National Laboratory's Communications and Community Outreach|accessdate=20 August 2013|quote=Oak Ridge at that time was so terribly bureaucratized that I am sorry to say I could not stand it.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Feeling unsuited to a managerial role in such an environment, he left Oak Ridge at the end of summer in 1947 and returned to Princeton University. He maintained a consulting role with the facility for many years.&lt;ref name=&quot;NAS&quot;/&gt; In the postwar period he served on a number of government bodies, including the [[National Bureau of Standards]] from 1947 to 1951, the mathematics panel of the [[United States National Research Council|National Research Council]] from 1951 to 1954, the physics panel of the [[National Science Foundation]], and the influential General Advisory Committee of the [[United States Atomic Energy Commission|Atomic Energy Commission]] from 1952 to 1957 and again from 1959 to 1964.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|p=270}} He also contributed to [[civil defense]].{{sfn|Szanton|1992|pp=288–290}}

In 1960, Wigner published a now classic article on the philosophy of mathematics and of physics, which has become his best-known work outside of technical mathematics and physics, ''[[The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Mathematics in the Natural Sciences]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;unreasonable&quot;&gt;{{cite doi|10.1002/cpa.3160130102}}&lt;/ref&gt; He argued that biology and cognition could be the origin of physical concepts, as we humans perceive them, and that the happy coincidence that mathematics and physics were so well matched, seemed to be &quot;unreasonable&quot; and hard to explain. His reasoning was resisted by the Harvard mathematician [[Andrew M. Gleason]].

In 1963, Wigner was awarded the [[Nobel Prize in Physics]]. He professed to never have considered the possibility that this might occur, and he added: &quot;I never expected to get my name in the newspapers without doing something wicked.&quot; Wigner also won the [[Enrico Fermi]] award in 1958, and the [[National Medal of Science]] in 1969. In 1968 he gave the [[Josiah Willard Gibbs]] lecture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ams.org/meetings/lectures/meet-gibbs-lect Josiah Willard Gibbs Lectures]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Problems of symmetry in old and new physics|journal=Bull. Amer. Math. Soc.|year=1968|volume=75|issue=5|pages=793–815|mr=1566474}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1992, at the age of 90, Wigner published a memoir, ''The Recollections of Eugene P. Wigner'' with [[Andrew Szanton]]. Wigner died three years later in [[Princeton, New Jersey]]. One of his significant students was [[Abner Shimony]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NAS&quot;/&gt; Wigner's third wife was Eileen Clare-Patton Hamilton Wigner (&quot;Pat&quot;) (1915–2010), the widow of another physicist, Donald Ross Hamilton, the Dean of the Graduate School at Princeton University who had died in 1972.{{sfn|Szanton|1992|p=305}}

Near the end of his life, Wigner's thoughts turned more philosophical. In his memoirs, Wigner said: &quot;The full meaning of life, the collective meaning of all human desires, is fundamentally a mystery beyond our grasp. As a young man, I chafed at this state of affairs. But by now I have made peace with it. I even feel a certain honor to be associated with such a mystery.&quot; He became interested in the [[Vedanta]] philosophy of [[Hinduism]], particularly its ideas of the universe as an all pervading [[consciousness]].  In his collection of essays ''Symmetries and Reflections – Scientific Essays'', he commented &quot;It was not possible to formulate the laws (of quantum theory) in a fully consistent way without reference to consciousness.&quot;

Wigner also conceived the ''[[Wigner's friend]]'' thought experiment in physics, which is an extension of the ''[[Schrödinger's cat]]'' thought experiment. The ''Wigner's friend'' experiment asks the question: &quot;At what stage does a 'measurement' take place?&quot; Wigner designed the experiment to highlight how he believed that consciousness is necessary to the quantum-mechanical measurement processes.

==Honors==
*[[Nobel Prize]], 1963
*[[Franklin Medal]], 1950
*[[Atoms for Peace Award]], 1959
*[http://www.ans.org/honors/va-wigner  Eugene P. Wigner Reactor Physicist Award] at the [[American Nuclear Society]].
*[http://www.sc.doe.gov/fermi/html/Laureates/1950s/eugenep.htm  Enrico Fermi Award].
*[http://www.ornl.gov/adm/wigner_fellowship/  Wigner Fellowship Program] at [[Oak Ridge National Laboratory]] (ORNL).
*[http://www.ornl.gov/ornlhome/print/press_release_print.cfm?ReleaseNumber=mr19960111-01 &quot;Auditorium at ORNL Renamed in Honor of Eugene P. Wigner&quot;] ORNL Press Release, (Jan. 11, 1996).

==Publications==
* 1958 (with [[Alvin M. Weinberg]]). ''Physical Theory of Neutron Chain Reactors'' (University of Chicago Press. ISBN 0-226-88517-8
* 1959. ''Group Theory and its Application to the Quantum Mechanics of Atomic Spectra''. New York: Academic Press. Translation by J. J. Griffin of 1931, ''Gruppentheorie und ihre Anwendungen auf die Quantenmechanik der Atomspektren'', Vieweg Verlag, Braunschweig.
* 1959. ''[http://www.dartmouth.edu/~matc/MathDrama/reading/Wigner.html The unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics in the natural sciences]'', Richard Courant lecture in mathematical sciences delivered at New York University, May 11, 1959. Communications on Pure and Applied Mathematics 13: 1–14. doi:10.1002/cpa.3160130102
* 1967. ''Symmetries and Reflections: Scientific Essays''. Indiana University Press, Bloomington. 1970, MIT Press. ISBN 0-262-73021-9
* 1992 (as told to Andrew Szanton). ''The Recollections of Eugene P. Wigner''. Plenum. ISBN 0-306-44326-0
* 1997 (with G. G. Emch; Jagdish Mehra and Arthur S. Wightman, eds.). ''Philosophical Reflections and Syntheses''. Springer. ISBN 3-540-63372-3

==See also==
* [[List of things named after Eugene Wigner]]
* [[Wigner rotation]]
* [[Wigner quasi-probability distribution]]
* [[Wigner semicircle distribution]]
* [[Particle physics and representation theory]]
* [[Wigner effect]]
* [[Wigner–Seitz cell]]
* [[Wigner 3-j symbols]]
* [[The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Mathematics in the Natural Sciences]]
* [[List of Jewish Nobel laureates]]
*  Wigner-İnönü [[group contraction]]
* [[Wigner–Eckart theorem]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book |first=Andrew |last=Szanton |authorlink=Andrew Szanton |title=The Recollections of Eugene P. Wigner|publisher=Plenum |year=1992 |isbn=0-306-44326-0 |ref=harv}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |authorlink=John Polkinghorne |first=John |last=Polkinghorne |title=Rochester Roundabout: the story of High Energy Physics |location=London |publisher=Longman |year=1989 |isbn=0-582-05011-1}}
* {{cite book |last=Rhodes|first=Richard |authorlink=Richard Rhodes |title=Dark Sun: The Making Of The Hydrogen Bomb |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |year=1996 |isbn=0-684-82414-0 }}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://alsos.wlu.edu/qsearch.aspx?browse=people/Wigner,+Eugene Annotated bibliography for Eugene Wigner from the Alsos Digital Library for Nuclear Issues]
*[http://www.osti.gov/accomplishments/wigner.html Biography and Bibliographic Resources], from the [[Office of Scientific and Technical Information]], [[United States Department of Energy]]
* [http://www.nobel-winners.com/Physics/eugene_paul_wigner.html Eugene Wigner Biography]
* [http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1963/wigner-bio.html Nobel Prize Biography]
* {{MacTutor Biography|id=Wigner}}
* {{MathGenealogy|id=36900}}
* {{Wayback |date=20110709032400 |url=http://geratorp.bravehost.com/dmx/wigner-bio.html |title=EPW contributions to the theory of the atomic nucleus and the elementary particles, particularly through the discovery and application of fundamental symmetry principles }}
* [http://www.princeton.edu/~mudd/finding_aids/mathoral/pmc44.htm 1984 interview with Wigner, in: The Princeton University Mathematics Community in the 1930s.]
* [http://www.aip.org/history/ohilist/4963_1.html Oral history interview transcript with Eugene Wigner 21 November 1963, American Institute of Physics, Niels Bohr Library &amp; Archives]
* [http://www.aip.org/history/ohilist/4965.html Oral history interview transcript with Eugene Wigner 24 January 1981, American Institute of Physics, Niels Bohr Library &amp; Archives]
* [http://www.kfki.hu/fszemle/archivum/fsz0702/radnai0702.html Wigner Jenö Iskolás Évei by Radnai Gyula, ELTE, Fizikai Szemle 2007/2 – 62.o. (''Hungarian'')]. Description of the childhood and especially of the school-years in Budapest, with some interesting photos too.
* [http://jewish.hu/view.php?clabel=wigner_jeno List of famous Hungarian Jews – Jenő Wigner]
* [http://purl.umn.edu/107714 Interview with Eugene P. Wigner on John von Neumann] at the  [[Charles Babbage Institute]], University of Minnesota, Minneapolis – Wigner talks about his association with [[John von Neumann]] during their school years in Hungary, their graduate studies in Berlin, and their appointments to Princeton in 1930. Wigner discusses von Neumann's contributions to the theory of quantum mechanics, Wigner's own work in this area, and von Neumann's interest in the application of theory to the atomic bomb project.

{{Authority control |VIAF=108474833 |LCCN=n/50/15686 }}
{{Nobel Prize in Physics Laureates 1951–1975}}
{{Hungarian Nobel Laureates}}
{{Presidents of the American Physical Society}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Wigner, Eugene Paul
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Wigner, E. P. (professional name); Wigner Pál Jenő (Hungarian)
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Mathematician and Nobel Prize-winning physicist
|DATE OF BIRTH=November 17, 1902
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Budapest]], [[Austria-Hungary]]
|DATE OF DEATH=January 1, 1995
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Princeton, New Jersey|Princeton]], [[New Jersey]], U.S.
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Wigner, Eugene Paul}}
[[Category:1902 births]]
[[Category:1995 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century mathematicians]]
[[Category:American atheists]]
[[Category:American Lutherans]]
[[Category:American physicists]]
[[Category:American Nobel laureates]]
[[Category:American people of Hungarian-Jewish descent]]
[[Category:Atoms for Peace Award recipients]]
[[Category:Technical University of Berlin alumni]]
[[Category:Burials at Princeton Cemetery]]
[[Category:Converts to Christianity from Judaism]]
[[Category:Enrico Fermi Award recipients]]
[[Category:Foreign Members of the Royal Society]]
[[Category:Hungarian emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Hungarian atheists]]
[[Category:Hungarian Jews]]
[[Category:Hungarian Lutherans]]
[[Category:Hungarian mathematicians]]
[[Category:Hungarian Nobel laureates]]
[[Category:Hungarian physicists]]
[[Category:Hungarian nuclear physicists]]
[[Category:Jewish American scientists]]
[[Category:Jewish atheists]]
[[Category:Jewish physicists]]
[[Category:Manhattan Project people]]
[[Category:Mathematical physicists]]
[[Category:Mystics]]
[[Category:National Medal of Science laureates]]
[[Category:Nobel laureates in Physics]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge National Laboratory people]]
[[Category:People from Pest, Hungary]]
[[Category:Princeton University faculty]]
[[Category:Theoretical physicists]]
[[Category:University of Göttingen faculty]]
[[Category:University of Wisconsin–Madison faculty]]
[[Category:Winners of the Max Planck Medal]]</text>
      <sha1>bfr94mxohui7qjgc6jc8v26t7y2u59q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>
    <title>Edmund Burke</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10030</id>
    <revision>
      <id>625828547</id>
      <parentid>624898693</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-16T16:01:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bluerasberry</username>
        <id>7830073</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Legacy */ connect main article here...</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Burkean|usage in literary theory|Kenneth Burke}}
{{Other people}}
{{EngvarB|date=August 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2013}}
{{Infobox philosopher
| name = Edmund Burke
| region = Western philosophy
| era = [[18th century philosophy]]
| image = EdmundBurke1771.jpg
| caption = Burke [[Circa|c.]] 1767/69, from the studio of [[Joshua Reynolds]] {{smaller|(1723–1792)}}.
| birth_date = 12 January 1729
| birth_place = [[Dublin]], [[Kingdom of Ireland|Ireland]]
| death_date  = {{Death date|1797|7|9|df=y}}
| death_place = [[Beaconsfield]], [[Buckinghamshire]], [[Kingdom of Great Britain|{{nowrap|Great Britain}}]]
| school_tradition = [[Liberal conservatism]]
| main_interests = Social and political philosophy
| influences =
 {{hlist |[[Aristotle]] |[[Cicero]] |[[John Locke]]}}
 {{hlist |[[Richard Hooker]] |[[Edward Coke]]}}
 {{hlist |[[Montesquieu]] |[[Sir William Blackstone|William Blackstone]]}}
| influenced =
 {{hlist |[[Robert Peel]] |[[Immanuel Kant]] |[[William Godwin]]}}
 {{hlist |[[John Dalberg-Acton, 1st Baron Acton|Lord Acton]] |[[William Ewart Gladstone]]}}
 {{hlist |[[Russell Kirk]] |[[Karl Popper]] |[[Friedrich Hayek]]}}
 {{hlist |[[Roger Scruton]] |[[Joseph de Maistre]]}}
 {{hlist |[[Hannah Arendt]] |[[William F. Buckley]]}}
 {{hlist |[[Matthew Arnold]]}}
 {{hlist |[[William Butler Yeats]] | [[Peter Hitchens]]}}
| notable_ideas =
}}

'''Edmund Burke''' [[Privy Council of Great Britain|PC]] (12 January &lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[New Style|NS]]&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; 1729&lt;!--
  --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The exact year of his birth is the subject of a great deal of controversy; 1728, 1729 and 1730 have been proposed. His date of birth is also subject to question, a problem compounded by the [[Julian calendar|Julian]]-[[Gregorian calendar|Gregorian]] changeover in 1752, during his lifetime. For a fuller treatment of the question, see F. P. Lock, ''Edmund Burke. Volume I: 1730–1784'' (Clarendon Press, 1999), pp. 16–17. [[Conor Cruise O'Brien]] (2008; p. 14) questions Burke's birthplace as having been in Dublin, arguing in favour of Shanballymore, Co. Cork (in the house of his uncle, James Nagle).&lt;!--
 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;{{spaced ndash}}9 July 1797) was an Irish&lt;!--
 --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Clark |first=J. C. D. |authorlink=J. C. D. Clark |title=Edmund Burke: Reflections on the Revolution in France: a Critical Edition |publisher=Stanford |page=25 |year=2001 |isbn=0-8047-3923-4 |quote=Edmund Burke was an Irishman, born in Dublin but in an age before 'Celtic nationalism' had been constructed to make Irishness and Englishness incompatible: he was therefore free also to describe himself, without misrepresentation, as 'a loyalist being loyal to England' to denote his membership of the wider polity. He never attempted to disguise his Irishness (as some ambitious Scots in eighteenth-century England tried to anglicise their accents), did what he could in the Commons to promote the interests of his native country and was bitterly opposed to the Penal Laws against Irish Catholics.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Christopher |last=Hitchens |authorlink=Christopher Hitchens |title=Reactionary Prophet |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/2004/04/hitchens.htm |newspaper=The Atlantic |location=Washington |date=April 2004 |quote=Edmund Burke was neither an Englishman nor a Tory. He was an Irishman, probably a Catholic Irishman at that (even if perhaps a secret sympathiser), and for the greater part of his life he upheld the more liberal principles of the Whig faction.}}&lt;!--
  --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; statesman born in Dublin; author, [[orator]], political theorist and philosopher, who, after moving to England, served for many years in the [[House of Commons of Great Britain]] as a member of the [[Whig (British political party)|Whig]] party.

He is mainly remembered for his support of the cause of the [[American Revolution]]aries, and for his later opposition to the [[French Revolution]]. The latter led to his becoming the leading figure within the conservative faction of the [[Whig (British political party)|Whig party]], which he dubbed the &quot;Old Whigs&quot;, in opposition to the pro–French Revolution &quot;New Whigs&quot;, led by [[Charles James Fox]].&lt;ref&gt;Burke lived before the terms &quot;conservative&quot; and &quot;liberal&quot; were used to describe political ideologies, cf. J. C. D. Clark, ''English Society, 1660–1832'' ([[Cambridge University Press]], 2000), p. 5, p. 301.&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke was praised by both [[conservativism|conservatives]] and [[Liberalism|liberals]] in the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author1=Dennis O'Keeffe |author2=John Meadowcroft |title=Edmund Burke |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YVO9QuYUGwwC&amp;pg=PA93 |year=2009 |publisher=Continuum |page=93}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the 20th century, he has generally been viewed as the philosophical founder of modern conservatism.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Heywood, ''Political Ideologies: An Introduction. Third Edition'' (Palgrave Macmillan, 2003), p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;F. P. Lock, ''Edmund Burke. Volume II: 1784–1797'' (Clarendon Press, 2006), p. 585.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early life ==
Burke was born in [[Dublin]], [[Ireland]], to a prosperous solicitor father Richard; (died 1761) of the [[Church of Ireland]]. It is unclear if this is the same Richard Burke who converted from Catholicism.&lt;ref&gt;J. C. D. Clark (ed.), ''Reflections on the Revolution in France. A Critical Edition'' ([[Stanford University Press]], 2001), p. 26, n. 13. Hereafter cited as &quot;Clark&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot;&gt;Paul Langford, [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/4019 Burke, Edmund (1729/30–1797)], ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'', Oxford University Press, September 2004; online edn, January 2008, accessed 18 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; His mother Mary (c. 1702 – 1770), whose maiden name was Nagle, was a [[Roman Catholic]] and came from an impoverished but genteel [[County Cork]] family. The [[House of Burke|Burke dynasty]] descended from an Anglo-Norman surnamed de Burgh (Latinised as de Burgo) who arrived in Ireland in 1185 following the [[Norman invasion of Ireland]] by [[Henry II of England]] in 1171.&lt;ref&gt;[[James Prior (surgeon)|James Prior]], ''Life of the Right Honourable Edmund Burke. Fifth Edition'' (London: Henry G. Bohn, 1854), p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke was raised in his father's faith and remained throughout his life a practising [[Anglicanism|Anglican]], unlike his sister Juliana who was brought up as and remained a Roman Catholic. His political enemies were later to repeatedly accuse him of having been educated at the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] [[College of St. Omer]], near [[Calais]], France and of harbouring secret Catholic sympathies at a time when membership of the Catholic Church would disqualify him from public office (''see'' [[Penal Laws (Ireland)|Penal Laws in Ireland]]). As Burke told [[Frances Crewe, Lady Crewe|Mrs. Crewe]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Mr. Burke's Enemies often endeavoured to convince the World that he had been bred up in the Catholic Faith, &amp; that his Family were of it, &amp; that he himself had been educated at St. Omer—but this was false, as his father was a regular practitioner of the Law at Dublin, which he could not be unless of the Established Church: &amp; it so happened that though Mr. B— was twice at Paris, he never happened to go through the Town of [[Saint-Omer|St. Omer]].&lt;ref&gt;'Extracts from Mr. Burke's Table-talk, at Crewe Hall. Written down by Mrs. Crewe, pp. 62.', ''Miscellanies of the Philobiblon Society. Volume VII'' (London: Whittingham and Wilkins, 1862–3), pp. 52–3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Once an MP, Burke was required to take the oath of allegiance and abjuration, the oath of supremacy, and declare against [[transubstantiation]]. No Catholic is known to have done so in the 18th century.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; He attended [[Trinity College Dublin]], a Protestant establishment, which up until 1793 did not permit Catholics to take degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;millbanksystems&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1834/may/08/catholics-and-trinity-college-dublin|title=CATHOLICS AND TRINITY COLLEGE, DUBLIN. (Hansard, 8 May 1834)|publisher=hansard.millbanksystems.com|accessdate=23 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although never denying his Irishness, Burke often described himself as &quot;an Englishman&quot;. According to historian [[J. C. D. Clark]], this was in an age &quot;before 'Celtic nationalism' sought to make Irishness and Englishness incompatible&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

As a child he sometimes spent time away from the unhealthy air of Dublin with his mother's family in the [[Munster Blackwater|Blackwater]] Valley in County Cork. He received his early education at a [[Quakers|Quaker]] school in [[Ballitore]], County Kildare, some {{convert|30|mi|km}} from Dublin, and remained in correspondence with his schoolmate [[Mary Leadbeater]], the daughter of the school's owner, throughout his life.

In 1744, Burke went to [[Trinity College, Dublin]] and, in 1747, set up a debating society, &quot;Edmund Burke's Club&quot;, which, in 1770, merged with the college's Historical Club to form the [[College Historical Society]], now the oldest undergraduate society in the world. The minutes of the meetings of Burke's club remain in the collection of the Historical Society. He graduated in 1748. Burke's father wished him to study for the law, and with this object he went to London in 1750. He entered the [[Middle Temple]], but soon gave up legal study to travel in Continental Europe. After giving up law, he attempted to earn a livelihood through writing.

===Early writing===
The late [[Henry St John, 1st Viscount Bolingbroke|Lord Bolingbroke]]'s ''Letters on the Study and Use of History'' was published in 1752 and his collected works appeared in 1754. This provoked Burke into writing his first published work, ''[[A Vindication of Natural Society|A Vindication of Natural Society: A View of the Miseries and Evils Arising to Mankind]]'', appearing in Spring 1756. Burke imitated Lord Bolingbroke's style and ideas in a ''[[reductio ad absurdum]]'' of his arguments for atheistic rationalism, demonstrating their absurdity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prior, p. 45&quot;&gt;Prior, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jim McCue, ''Edmund Burke and Our Present Discontents'' (The Claridge Press, 1997), p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Edmund Burke2 c.jpg|left|thumb|&quot;The writers against religion, whilst they oppose every system, are wisely careful never to set up any of their own.&quot; ''[[A Vindication of Natural Society]]''.]]

Burke claimed that Bolingbroke's arguments against revealed religion could apply to all social and civil institutions. [[Philip Stanhope, 4th Earl of Chesterfield|Lord Chesterfield]] and [[William Warburton|Bishop Warburton]] (and others) initially thought that the work was genuinely by Bolingbroke rather than a satire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prior, p. 45&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McCue, p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt; All the reviews of the work were positive, with critics especially appreciative of Burke's quality of writing. Some reviewers failed to notice the ironic nature of the book, which led to Burke writing in the preface to the second edition (1757) that it was a satire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. I, p. 85&quot;&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Richard Hurd (clergyman)|Richard Hurd]] believed that Burke's imitation was near-perfect and that this defeated his purpose: an ironist &quot;should take care by a constant exaggeration to make the ''ridicule'' shine through the Imitation. Whereas this ''Vindication'' is everywhere enforc'd, not only in the language, and on the principles of L. Bol., but with so apparent, or rather so real an earnestness, that half his purpose is sacrificed to the other&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. I, p. 85&quot; /&gt; A minority of scholars have taken the position that Burke did in fact write the ''Vindication'' in earnest, later disowning it only for political reasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lewrockwell.com/rothbard/rothbard11.html |title=Edmund Burke, Anarchist |accessdate=14 October 2007 |author=Rothbard, Murray}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Joseph Sobran|Sobran, Joseph]], [http://www.sobran.com/columns/2002/020124.shtml Anarchism, Reason, and History]: &quot;Oddly enough, the great conservative Edmund Burke began his career with an anarchist tract, arguing that the state was naturally and historically destructive of human society, life, and liberty. Later he explained that he'd intended his argument ironically, but many have doubted this. His argument for anarchy was too powerful, passionate, and cogent to be a joke. Later, as a professional politician, Burke seems to have come to terms with the state, believing that no matter how bloody its origins, it could be tamed and civilized, as in Europe, by &quot;the spirit of a gentleman, and the spirit of religion&quot;. But even as he wrote, the old order he loved was already breaking down. &quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1757, Burke published a treatise on aesthetics, ''[[A Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful]]'', which attracted the attention of prominent Continental thinkers such as [[Denis Diderot]] and [[Immanuel Kant]]. It was his only purely philosophical work, and when asked by [[Sir Joshua Reynolds]] and [[French Laurence]] to expand it thirty years later, Burke replied that he was no longer fit for abstract speculation (Burke had written it before he was 19).&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 February 1757, Burke signed a contract with [[Robert Dodsley]] to write a &quot;history of England from the time of Julius Caesar to the end of the reign of Queen Anne&quot;, its length being eighty quarto sheets (640 pages), under 400,000 words. It was to be submitted for publication by Christmas 1758.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke actually completed to the year 1216, and never published the work. It was not published until 1812 in Burke's collected works under the title of ''An Essay Towards an Abridgement of the English History'', after Burke's death. [[G. M. Young]] did not value Burke's history and claimed that it was &quot;demonstrably a translation from the French&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;G. M. Young, 'Burke', ''Proceedings of the British Academy'', XXIX (London, 1943), p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lord Acton]], on commenting on the story that Burke stopped his history because [[David Hume]] published his, said &quot;it is ever to be regretted that the reverse did not occur&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Herbert Butterfield, ''Man on His Past'' (Cambridge, 1955), p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

The following year, with Dodsley, Burke created the influential ''[[Annual Register]]'', a publication in which various authors evaluated the international political events of the previous year.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, pp. 52–3.&lt;/ref&gt; The extent to which Burke personally contributed to the ''Annual Register'' is contested.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Wellsted Copeland, 'Edmund Burke and the Book Reviews in Dodsley's Annual Register', ''Publications of the [[Modern Language Association]]'', Vol. 57, No. 2. (Jun. 1942), pp. 446–468.&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Murray in his biography of Burke quotes the ''Register'' as evidence of Burke's opinions, yet Philip Magnus in his biography does not directly cite it as a reference.&lt;ref name=&quot;Copeland, p. 446&quot;&gt;Copeland, p. 446.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke remained its chief editor until at least 1789 and there is no evidence that any other writer contributed to it before 1766.&lt;ref name=&quot;Copeland, p. 446&quot; /&gt;

On 12 March 1757, Burke married Jane Mary Nugent (1734–1812), daughter of a Catholic physician who had treated him at [[Bath, Somerset|Bath]]. Their son [[Richard Burke Jr.|Richard]] was born on 9 February 1758. Another son, Christopher, died in infancy. Burke also helped raise a ward, [[Edmund Nagle]] (later Admiral [[Sir Edmund Nagle]]), the son of a cousin orphaned in 1763.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot;&gt;[http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/19720 Nagle, Sir Edmund], ''[[Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]]'', [[John Knox Laughton|J. K. Laughton]], (subscription required), Retrieved 22 April 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

At about this same time, Burke was introduced to [[William Gerard Hamilton]] (known as &quot;Single-speech Hamilton&quot;). When Hamilton was appointed [[Chief Secretary for Ireland]], Burke accompanied him to Dublin as his private secretary, a position he maintained for three years. In 1765 Burke became private secretary to liberal Whig statesman [[Charles Watson-Wentworth, 2nd Marquess of Rockingham|Charles Watson-Wentworth]], the [[Marquess of Rockingham]], at the time Prime Minister of Great Britain, who remained Burke's close friend and associate until his premature death in 1782. Burke was a Freemason.&lt;ref&gt;Denslow, William R., 10,000 Famous Freemasons, 4 vol., Missouri Lodge of Research, Trenton, Missouri, 1957–61. volume 1, page 155&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://freemasonry.bcy.ca/biography/burke_e/burke_e.html |title=Edmund Burke |publisher=Freemasonry.bcy.ca |date= |accessdate=28 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Member of Parliament ==
{{The Club|size=250px|align=right}}

In December 1765, Burke entered the [[Parliament of Great Britain|British Parliament]] as a member of the House of Commons for [[Wendover (UK Parliament constituency)|Wendover]], a [[pocket borough]] in the control of Lord Fermanagh, later 2nd [[Earl Verney]], a close political ally of Rockingham. After Burke's [[maiden speech]], [[William Pitt, 1st Earl of Chatham|William Pitt the Elder]] said Burke had &quot;spoken in such a manner as to stop the mouths of all Europe&quot; and that the Commons should congratulate itself on acquiring such a member.&lt;ref&gt;McCue, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first great subject in which Burke interested himself was the controversy with the American colonies, which soon developed into war and ultimate separation; in 1769 he published, in reply to [[George Grenville|Grenvillite]] pamphlet ''The Present State of the Nation'', his pamphlet on ''Observations on a Late State of the Nation''. Surveying the finances of France, Burke predicts &quot;some extraordinary convulsion in that whole system&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 262.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the same year, Burke purchased ''Gregories''{{spaced ndash}}a {{convert|600|acre|km2|1|sing=on}} estate near [[Beaconsfield]]{{spaced ndash}}with mostly borrowed money. Although it included saleable assets such as art works by [[Titian]], ''Gregories'' was a heavy financial burden in the following decades and Burke was never able to pay in full for the estate. His speeches and writings had now made him famous, and among other effects had brought about the suggestion that he was the author of the ''[[Letters of Junius]]''.

At about this time, Burke joined the circle of leading intellectuals, and artists in London with [[Samuel Johnson]] as its central luminary, also including [[David Garrick]], [[Oliver Goldsmith]], and [[Joshua Reynolds]]. [[Edward Gibbon]] described him as 'the most eloquent and rational madman that I ever knew.'&lt;ref&gt;''Private Letters of Edward Gibbon, II (1896)'' Prothero, P. (ed.). p. 251 cited in ''The Decline and Fall of the British Empire: 1781–1998'' (2007) Brendon, Piers. Jonathan Cape, London. p. 10 ISBN 978-0-224-06222-0&lt;/ref&gt; Although Johnson admired Burke's brilliance, he found him a dishonest politician.&lt;ref&gt;Boswell, ''Life of Samuel Johnson'', edited by Hill-Powell; v. II, p. 349; 7 April 1775&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Boswell, Journals, ''Boswell: The Ominous Years'', p. 134, edited by Ryskamp &amp; Pottle; McGraw Hill, 1963&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke took a leading role in the debate over the constitutional limits to the executive authority of the King. He argued strongly against unrestrained royal power and for the role of political parties in maintaining a principled opposition capable of preventing abuses, either by the monarch or by specific factions within the government. His most important publication in this regard was his ''Thoughts on the Cause of the Present Discontents'' of 23 April 1770.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.econlib.org/library/LFBooks/Burke/brkSWv1c1.html |title=Burke: Select Works of Edmund Burke, Vol. 1, Thoughts on the Cause of the Present Discontents: Library of Economics and Liberty |publisher=Econlib.org |accessdate=4 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Burke identified the &quot;discontents&quot; as stemming from the &quot;secret influence&quot; of a neo-Tory group he calls the &quot;king's friends&quot;, whose system &quot;comprehending the exterior and interior Administrations, is commonly called, in the technical language of the Court, ''Double Cabinet''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 277.&lt;/ref&gt; Britain needed a party with &quot;an unshaken adherence to principle, and attachment to connexion, against every allurement of interest&quot;. Party divisions &quot;whether operating for good or evil, are things inseparable from free government&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 283.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Gregories Estate near Beaconsfield Buckinghamshire 1792.jpg|thumb|The ''Gregories'' estate, purchased by Burke for £20,000 in 1768.]]
During 1771, Burke wrote a Bill that would have, if passed, given juries the right to determine what was libel. Burke spoke in favour of the Bill but it was opposed by some, including Charles James Fox, and was not passed. Fox, when introducing [[Libel Act 1792|his own Bill]] in 1791, repeated almost verbatim the text of Burke's Bill without acknowledgement.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 127 + pp. 340–2.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke was also prominent in securing the right to publish debates held in Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt;

Speaking in a parliamentary debate on the prohibition on the export of grain on 16 November 1770, Burke argued in favour of a free market in corn: &quot;There are no such things as a high, &amp; a low price that is encouraging, &amp; discouraging; there is nothing but a natural price, which grain brings at an universal market.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', pp. 321–22.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1772 Burke was instrumental in passing the [[Repeal of Certain Laws Act 1772]], which repealed various old laws against dealers and forestallers in corn.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 322.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the ''Annual Register'' for 1772 (published in July 1773), Burke condemned the [[First Partition of Poland|Partition of Poland]]. He saw it as &quot;the first very great breach in the modern political system of Europe&quot; and upsetting the balance of power in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[[Brendan Simms]], ''Three Victories and a Defeat. The Rise and Fall of the First British Empire, 1714–1783'' (Allen Lane, 2007), pp. 569–71.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1774, Burke was elected member for [[Bristol (UK Parliament constituency)|Bristol]], at the time &quot;England's second city&quot; and a large constituency with a genuine electoral contest.

In May 1778, Burke supported a motion in Parliament to revise the restrictions on Irish trade. However his constituents in Bristol, a great trading city, urged Burke to oppose free trade with Ireland. Burke resisted these demands and said: &quot;If, from this conduct, I shall forfeit their suffrages at an ensuing election, it will stand on record an example to future representatives of the Commons of England, that one man at least had dared to resist the desires of his constituents when his judgment assured him they were wrong&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke published ''Two Letters to Gentlemen of Bristol on the Bills relative to the Trade of Ireland'', in which he espoused &quot;some of the chief principles of commerce; such as the advantage of free intercourse between all parts of the same kingdom...the evils attending restriction and monopoly...and that the gain of others is not necessarily our loss, but on the contrary an advantage by causing a greater demand for such wares as we have for sale&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, pp. 175–6.&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke also supported [[Sir George Savile, 8th Baronet|Sir George Savile]]'s attempts to repeal some of the [[penal laws]] against Catholics.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt; He also called capital punishment &quot;the Butchery which we call justice&quot; in 1776 and in 1780 Burke condemned the use of the [[pillory]] for two men convicted for attempting to practice sodomy.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot; /&gt;

This support for unpopular causes, notably free trade with Ireland and [[Catholic Emancipation]], led to Burke losing his seat in 1780. For the remainder of his parliamentary career, Burke sat for [[Malton (UK Parliament constituency)|Malton]], another pocket borough controlled by [[Charles Watson-Wentworth, 2nd Marquess of Rockingham|the Marquess of Rockingham]].

== American War of Independence ==
Burke expressed his support for the grievances of the [[American Colonies]] under the government of [[King George III]] and his appointed representatives. On 19 April 1774 Burke made a [[On American Taxation|speech]] (published in January 1775) on a motion to repeal the tea duty:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Again and again, revert to your old principles—seek peace and ensue it; leave America, if she has taxable matter in her, to tax herself. I am not here going into the distinctions of rights, nor attempting to mark their boundaries. I do not enter into these metaphysical distinctions; I hate the very sound of them. Leave the Americans as they anciently stood, and these distinctions, born of our unhappy contest, will die along with it. ... Be content to bind America by laws of trade; you have always done it. ... Do not burthen them with taxes. ... But if intemperately, unwisely, fatally, you sophisticate and poison the very source of government by urging subtle deductions, and consequences odious to those you govern, from the unlimited and illimitable nature of supreme sovereignty, you will teach them by these means to call that sovereignty itself in question. ... If that sovereignty and their freedom cannot be reconciled, which will they take? They will cast your sovereignty in your face. No body of men will be argued into slavery. Sir, let the gentlemen on the other side ... tell me, what one character of liberty the Americans have, and what one brand of slavery they are free from, if they are bound in their property and industry by all the restraints you can imagine on commerce, and at the same time are made pack-horses of every tax you choose to impose, without the least share in granting them. When they bear the burthens of unlimited monopoly, will you bring them to bear the burthens of unlimited revenue too? The Englishman in America will feel that this is slavery; that it is ''legal'' slavery, will be no compensation either to his feelings or to his understandings.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, pp. 142–3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On 22 March 1775, in the House of Commons, Burke delivered a speech (published in May 1775) on reconciliation with America. Burke appealed for peace as preferable to civil war and reminded the House of America's growing population, its industry and its wealth. He warned against the notion that the Americans would back down in the face of force, as the Americans were descended largely from Englishmen:

&lt;blockquote&gt;... the people of the colonies are descendants of Englishmen. ... They are therefore not only devoted to liberty, but to liberty according to English ideas and on English principles. The people are Protestants ... a persuasion not only favourable to liberty, but built upon it. ... My hold of the colonies is in the close affection which grows from common names, from kindred blood, from similar privileges, and equal protection. These are ties which, though light as air, are as strong as links of iron. Let the colonies always keep the idea of their civil rights associated with your government—they will cling and grapple to you, and no force under heaven will be of power to tear them from their allegiance. But let it be once understood that your government may be one thing and their privileges another, that these two things may exist without any mutual relation—the cement is gone, the cohesion is loosened, and everything hastens to decay and dissolution. As long as you have the wisdom to keep the sovereign authority of this country as the sanctuary of liberty, the sacred temple consecrated to our common faith, wherever the chosen race and sons of England worship freedom, they will turn their faces towards you. The more they multiply, the more friends you will have; the more ardently they love liberty, the more perfect will be their obedience. Slavery they can have anywhere. It is a weed that grows in every soil. They may have it from Spain, they may have it from Prussia. But, until you become lost to all feeling of your true interest and your natural dignity, freedom they can have from none but you.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/15198/15198-h/15198-h.htm |title=Speech on Moving Resolutions for Conciliation with America, 22 March 1775 |publisher=Gutenberg.org |date= |accessdate=28 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

One of the reasons why this speech was so admired was the passage on [[Allen Bathurst, 1st Earl Bathurst|Lord Bathurst]] (1684–1775). Burke imagines an angel in 1704 prophesying to Bathurst the future greatness of England and also of America: &quot;Young man, There is America—which at this day serves little more than to amuse you with stories of savage men, and uncouth manners; yet shall, before you taste of death, shew itself equal to the whole of that commerce which now attracts the envy of the world&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. I, p. 384&quot;&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 384.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Samuel Johnson]] was so irritated at hearing it continually praised that he made a parody of it, where the devil appears to a young Whig and predicts that [[Whiggism]] will in short time poison even the paradise of America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. I, p. 384&quot; /&gt;

The administration of [[Frederick North, Lord North|Lord North]] (1770–1782) tried to defeat the colonists' rebellion by military force. British and American forces clashed in 1775 and in 1776 came the [[United States Declaration of Independence|American Declaration of Independence]]. Burke was appalled by celebrations in Britain of the defeat of the Americans at New York and Pennsylvania. He claimed the English national character was being changed by this authoritarianism.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot; /&gt; Burke wrote: &quot;As to the good people of England, they seem to partake every day more and more of the Character of that administration which they have been induced to tolerate. I am satisfied, that within a few years there has been a great Change in the National Character. We seem no longer that eager, inquisitive, jealous, fiery people, which we have been formerly&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 394.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Burke's view, the British government was fighting &quot;the American English&quot; (&quot;our English Brethren in the Colonies&quot;), with a German-descended King employing &quot;the hireling sword of German boors and vassals&quot; to destroy the colonists' English liberties.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot; /&gt; On American independence, Burke wrote: &quot;I do not know how to wish success to those whose Victory is to separate from us a large and noble part of our Empire. Still less do I wish success to injustice, oppression and absurdity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 399.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1780, during the [[Gordon Riots]], Burke became a target and his home was placed under armed guard by the military.&lt;ref&gt;Hibbert pp. 48–73&lt;/ref&gt;

== Paymaster of the Forces ==
[[File:Cincinnatus in retirement.jpg|thumb|300px|In ''Cincinnatus in Retirement'' (1782), [[James Gillray]] caricatured Burke's support of rights for Catholics.]]

The fall of North led to Rockingham being recalled to power in March 1782. Burke became [[Paymaster of the Forces]] and a [[Privy Council of the United Kingdom|Privy Councillor]], but without a seat in the Cabinet. Rockingham's unexpected death in July 1782 and his replacement as Prime Minister by Shelburne put an end to his administration after only a few months. However, Burke did manage to pass two Acts.

The [[Paymaster General Act 1782]] ended the post as a lucrative sinecure. Previously, Paymasters had been able to draw on money from the Treasury at their discretion. Now they were to put the money they had requested to withdraw from the Treasury into the Bank of England, from where it was to be withdrawn for specific purposes. The Treasury would receive monthly statements of the Paymaster's balance at the Bank. This Act was repealed by Shelburne's administration but the Act that replaced it repeated verbatim almost the whole text of Burke's Act.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', p. 511 + n. 65.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Civil List and Secret Service Money Act 1782]] was a watered down version of Burke's original intentions as outlined in his famous ''Speech on Economical Reform'' of 11 February 1780. However he managed to abolish 134 offices in the royal household and civil administration.&lt;ref&gt;McCue, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; The third [[Secretary of State (United Kingdom)|Secretary of State]] and the [[Board of Trade]] were abolished and pensions were limited and regulated. The Act was projected to save £72,368 a year.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. I'', pp. 511–2.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 1783, Burke resumed the post of Paymaster of the Forces when Shelburne's government fell and was replaced by a coalition headed by North and including Charles James Fox. The coalition fell in 1783, and was succeeded by the long Tory administration of [[William Pitt the Younger]], which lasted until 1801. Burke, who had supported Fox and North, was accordingly in opposition for the remainder of his political life.

== Democracy ==
In 1774, Burke's ''Speech to the Electors at Bristol at the Conclusion of the Poll'' was noted for its defence of the principles of [[Representation (politics)|representative]] government against the notion that elected officials should merely be delegates:

&lt;blockquote&gt;... it ought to be the happiness and glory of a representative to live in the strictest union, the closest correspondence, and the most unreserved communication with his constituents. Their wishes ought to have great weight with him; their opinion, high respect; their business, unremitted attention. It is his duty to sacrifice his repose, his pleasures, his satisfactions, to theirs; and above all, ever, and in all cases, to prefer their interest to his own. But his unbiased opinion, his mature judgment, his enlightened conscience, he ought not to sacrifice to you, to any man, or to any set of men living. These he does not derive from your pleasure; no, nor from the law and the constitution. They are a trust from Providence, for the abuse of which he is deeply answerable. Your representative owes you, not his industry only, but his judgment; and he betrays, instead of serving you, if he sacrifices it to your opinion.&lt;ref&gt;''The Works of the Right Honourable Edmund Burke. Volume I'' (London: Henry G. Bohn, 1854), pp. 446–8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Political scientist [[Hanna Pitkin]] points out that Burke linked the district's interest with the proper behaviour of its elected official, explaining, &quot;Burke conceives of broad, relatively fixed interest, few in number and clearly defined, of which any group or locality has just one. These interests are largely economic or associated with particular localities whose livelihood they characterize, in his over-all prosperity they involve.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hanna Fenichel Pitkin, ''The concept of representation'' (1972) p. 174&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke was a leading sceptic with respect to democracy. While admitting that theoretically in some cases it might be desirable, he insisted a democratic government in Britain in his day would not only be inept but also oppressive. He opposed democracy for three basic reasons. First, government required a degree of intelligence and breadth of knowledge of the sort that was very uncommon among the common people. Second, he thought that common people had dangerous and angry passions that could be easily aroused by demagogues if they had the vote; he feared the authoritarian impulses that could be empowered by these passions would undermine cherished traditions and established religion, leading to violence and confiscation of property. Third, Burke warned that democracy would [[Tyranny of the majority|tyrannise unpopular minorities]] who needed the protection of the upper classes.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Hamburger, &quot;Burke, Edmund&quot; in Seymour Martin Lipset, ed., ''The Encyclopedia of Democracy'' (Congressional Quarterly, 1995) 1:147–149&lt;/ref&gt;

== India and the impeachment of Warren Hastings ==
{{main|Impeachment of Warren Hastings}}

Burke pursued for years the impeachment against [[Warren Hastings]], the former Governor General of Bengal, in 1786. His interaction with the British dominion of India began well before the impeachment trial. Prior to the impeachment, Parliament had dealt with the Indian issue for two decades. This trial was the pinnacle of years of unrest and deliberation.&lt;ref&gt;Siraj Ahmed, &quot;The Theater of the Civilized Self: Edmund Burke and the East India Trials&quot;. ''[[Representations]]'' 78 (2002): 30.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1781 Burke was first able to delve into the issues surrounding the [[East India Company]] when he was appointed Chairman of the Commons' Select Committee on East Indian Affair—from that point until the end of the trial; India was Burke's primary concern. This committee was charged &quot;to investigate alleged injustices in Bengal, the war with Hyder Ali, and other Indian difficulties&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Russell Kirk, ''Edmund Burke: A Genius Reconsidered'' (1988), 2.&lt;/ref&gt; While Burke and the committee focused their attention on these matters, a second 'secret' committee was formed to assess the same issues. Both committee reports were written by Burke. Among other purposes, the reports conveyed to the Indian princes that Britain would not wage war on them, along with demanding that the EIC recall Hastings. This was Burke's first call for substantive change regarding imperial practices. When addressing the whole House of Commons in regards to the Committee's report, Burke described the Indian issue as one that &quot;began 'in commerce' but 'ended in empire.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth D. Samet, &quot;A Prosecutor and a Gentleman: Edmund Burke's Idiom of Impeachment&quot;, ''[[ELH]]'' 68, no. 2 (2001): 402.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 February 1785, Burke delivered a now-famous speech on ''The [[Nabob of Arcot]]'s Debts'', wherein he condemned the damage  done unto [[India]] by the East India Company. In the province of the [[Carnatic region|Carnatic]] the Indians had constructed a system of reservoirs to make the soil fertile in a naturally dry region, and centred their society on the husbandry of water:

&lt;blockquote&gt;These are the monuments of real kings, who were the fathers of their people; testators to a posterity which they embraced as their own. These are the grand sepulchres built by ambition; but by the ambition of an insatiable benevolence, which, not contented with reigning in the dispensation of happiness during the contracted term of human life, had strained, with all the reachings and graspings of a vivacious mind, to extend the dominion of their bounty beyond the limits of nature, and to perpetuate themselves through generations of generations, the guardians, the protectors, the nourishers of mankind.&lt;ref&gt;McCue, p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Burke held that the advent of British dominion, and in particular the conduct of the East India Company had destroyed much that was good in these traditions and that, as a consequence of this, and the lack of new customs to replace them, the Indians were suffering. He set about establishing a set of British expectations, whose moral foundation would, in his opinion, warrant the empire.&lt;ref&gt;McCue, p. 156.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 4 April 1786, Burke presented the Commons with the ''Article of Charge of [[High Crimes and Misdemeanors]]'' against Hastings. The [[impeachment]] in Westminster Hall, which did not begin until 14 February 1788, would be the &quot;first major public discursive event of its kind in England&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Mithi Mukherjee, &quot;Justice, War, and the Imperium: India and Britain in Edmund Burke's Prosecutorial Speeches&quot;, ''Law and History Review'' 23, no. 3 (2005): 589.&lt;/ref&gt; bringing the morality and duty of imperialism to the forefront of the public's perception. Burke was already known for his eloquent rhetorical skills and his involvement in the trial only enhanced its popularity and significance.&lt;ref&gt;Mukherjee, ''Justice, War, and the Imperium'', 590.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke's indictment, fuelled by emotional indignation, branded Hastings a 'captain-general of iniquity'; who never dined without 'creating a famine'; whose heart was 'gangrened to the core', and who resembled both a 'spider of Hell' and a 'ravenous vulture devouring the carcasses of the dead'.&lt;ref&gt;Piers Brendon, ''The Decline and Fall of the British Empire: 1781–1998'' (London: Jonathan Cape, 2007), p. 35. ISBN 978-0-224-06222-0&lt;/ref&gt; The House of Commons eventually [[Impeachment of Warren Hastings|impeached Hastings]], but the House of Lords subsequently acquitted him of all charges.

== French Revolution: 1688 versus 1789 ==
[[File:Smelling out a rat.jpg|thumb|''Smelling out a Rat;—or—The Atheistical-Revolutionist disturbed in his Midnight &quot;Calculations&quot;'' (1790) by Gillray, depicting a caricature of Burke with a long nose and spectacles, holding a crown and a cross. The seated man is Dr. Richard Price, who is writing &quot;On the Benefits of Anarchy Regicide Atheism&quot; beneath a picture of the execution of [[Charles I of England]].]]
[[File:BurkeReflections.jpg|thumb|''Reflections on the Revolution in France, And on the Proceedings in Certain Societies in London Relative to that Event. In a Letter Intended to Have Been Sent to a Gentleman in Paris. By the Right Honourable Edmund Burke.'']]

Initially, Burke did not condemn the [[French Revolution]]. In a letter of 9 August 1789, Burke wrote: &quot;England gazing with astonishment at a French struggle for Liberty and not knowing whether to blame or to applaud! The thing indeed, though I thought I saw something like it in progress for several years, has still something in it paradoxical and Mysterious. The spirit it is impossible not to admire; but the old Parisian ferocity has broken out in a shocking manner&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt; The events of 5–6 October 1789, in which a crowd of Parisian women marched on Versailles to compel [[Louis XVI of France|King Louis XVI]] to return to Paris, turned Burke against it. In a letter to his son Richard on 10 October he said: &quot;This day I heard from Laurence who has sent me papers confirming the portentous state of France—where the Elements which compose Human Society seem all to be dissolved, and a world of Monsters to be produced in the place of it—where Mirabeau presides as the Grand Anarch; and the late Grand Monarch makes a figure as ridiculous as pitiable&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, pp. 61–2.&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 November Charles-Jean-François Depont wrote to Burke, requesting that he endorse the Revolution. Burke replied that any critical language of it by him should be taken &quot;as no more than the expression of doubt&quot; but added: &quot;You may have subverted Monarchy, but not recover'd freedom&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; In the same month he described France as &quot;a country undone&quot;. Burke's first public condemnation of the Revolution occurred on the debate in Parliament on the Army Estimates on 9 February 1790, provoked by praise of the Revolution by Pitt and Fox:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Since the House had been prorogued in the summer much work was done in France. The French had shewn themselves the ablest architects of ruin that had hitherto existed in the world. In that very short space of time they had completely pulled down to the ground, their monarchy; their church; their nobility; their law; their revenue; their army; their navy; their commerce; their arts; and their manufactures...[there was a danger of] an imitation of the excesses of an irrational, unprincipled, proscribing, confiscating, plundering, ferocious, bloody and tyrannical democracy...[in religion] the danger of their example is no longer from intolerance, but from Atheism; a foul, unnatural vice, foe to all the dignity and consolation of mankind; which seems in France, for a long time, to have been embodied into a faction, accredited, and almost avowed.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, pp. 66–7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In January 1790, Burke read Dr. [[Richard Price]]'s sermon of 4 November 1789 to the [[Revolution Society]], called ''A Discourse on the Love of our Country''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.constitution.org/price/price_8.htm |title=A Discourse on the Love of our Country |publisher=Constitution.org |date= |accessdate=28 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Revolution Society was founded to commemorate the [[Glorious Revolution]] of 1688. In this sermon Price espoused the philosophy of universal &quot;rights of men&quot;. Price argued that love of our country &quot;does not imply any conviction of the superior value of it to other countries, or any particular preference of its laws and constitution of government&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, Englishmen should see themselves &quot;more as citizens of the world than as members of any particular community&quot;. The debate between Price and Burke was &quot;the classic moment at which two fundamentally different conceptions of national identity were presented to the English public&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, ''English Society'', p. 233.&lt;/ref&gt; Price claimed that the principles of the Glorious Revolution included &quot;the right to choose our own governors, to cashier them for misconduct, and to frame a government for ourselves&quot;. Immediately after reading Price's sermon, Burke wrote a draft of what eventually became the ''[[Reflections on the Revolution in France]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1086/241734 |title=The Genesis of Burke's Reflections |year=1978 |author=Dreyer, Frederick |journal=[[The Journal of Modern History]] |volume=50|issue=3 |page=462}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 February 1790, a notice in the press said that Burke would shortly publish a pamphlet on the Revolution and its British supporters, however he spent the year revising and expanding it. On 1 November he finally published the ''Reflections'' and it was an immediate best-seller.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 311.&lt;/ref&gt; Priced at five shillings, it was more expensive than most political pamphlets but by the end of 1790 it had gone through ten printings and sold approximately 17,500 copies. A French translation appeared on 29 November and on 30 November the translator, Pierre-Gaëton Dupont, wrote to Burke saying 2,500 copies had already been sold. The French translation ran to ten printings by June 1791.&lt;ref&gt;F. P. Lock, ''Burke's Reflections on the Revolution in France'' (London: Allen &amp; Unwin, 1985), p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt;

What the Glorious Revolution had meant was important to Burke and his contemporaries, as it had been for the last one hundred years in British politics.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''Reflections'', Burke argued against Price's interpretation of the Glorious Revolution and instead gave a classic Whig defence of it.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, pp. 24–5, p. 34, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke argued against the idea of abstract, metaphysical rights of men and instead advocated national tradition:

&lt;blockquote&gt; The Revolution was made to preserve our ''antient'' indisputable laws and liberties, and that ''antient'' constitution of government which is our only security for law and liberty.... The very idea of the fabrication of a new government, is enough to fill us with disgust and horror. We wished at the period of the Revolution, and do now wish, to derive all we possess as ''an inheritance from our forefathers''. Upon that body and stock of inheritance we have taken care not to inoculate any cyon [scion] alien to the nature of the original plant.... Our oldest reformation is that of [[Magna Carta|Magna Charta]]. You will see that Sir [[Edward Coke]], that great oracle of our law, and indeed all the great men who follow him, to [[William Blackstone|Blackstone]], are industrious to prove the pedigree of our liberties. They endeavour to prove that the ancient charter... were nothing more than a re-affirmance of the still more ancient standing law of the kingdom.... In the famous law... called the ''[[Petition of Right]]'', the parliament says to the king, &quot;Your subjects have ''inherited'' this freedom&quot;, claiming their franchises not on abstract principles &quot;as the rights of men&quot;, but as the rights of Englishmen, and as a patrimony derived from their forefathers.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, pp. 181–3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Burke put forward that &quot;We fear God, we look up with awe to kings; with affection to parliaments; with duty to magistrates; with reverence to priests; and with respect to nobility. Why? Because when such ideas are brought before our minds, it is ''natural'' to be so affected&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, pp. 250–1.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke defended prejudice on the grounds that it is &quot;the general bank and capital of nations, and of ages&quot; and superior to individual reason, which is small in comparison. &quot;Prejudice&quot;, Burke claimed, &quot;is of ready application in the emergency; it previously engages the mind in a steady course of wisdom and virtue, and does not leave the man hesitating in the moment of decision, skeptical, puzzled, and unresolved. Prejudice renders a man's virtue his habit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, pp. 251–2.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke criticised [[social contract]] theory by claiming that society is indeed a contract, but &quot;a partnership not only between those who are living, but between those who are living, those who are dead, and those who are to be born&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, p. 261.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most famous passage in Burke's ''Reflections'' was his description of the events of 5–6 October 1789 and [[Marie Antoinette]]'s part in them. Burke's account differs little from modern historians who have used primary sources.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', pp. 289–90.&lt;/ref&gt; His use of flowery language to describe it, however, provoked both praise and criticism. [[Philip Francis (politician)|Philip Francis]] wrote to Burke saying that what he wrote of Marie Antoinette was &quot;pure foppery&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Edward Gibbon]] however reacted differently: &quot;I adore his chivalry&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', p. 300.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke was informed by an Englishman who had talked with the Duchesse de Biron that when Marie Antoinette was reading the passage she burst into tears and took considerable time to finish reading it.&lt;ref&gt;Alfred Cobban and Robert A. Smith (eds.), ''The Correspondence of Edmund Burke. Volume VI'' (Cambridge University Press, 1967), p. 204.&lt;/ref&gt; Price had rejoiced that the French king had been &quot;led in triumph&quot; during the October Days but to Burke this symbolised the opposing revolutionary sentiment of the Jacobins and the natural sentiments of those like himself who regarded the ungallant assault on Marie Antoinette with horror, as a cowardly attack on a defenceless woman.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', p. 296.&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVI translated the ''Reflections'' &quot;from end to end&quot; into French.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, pp. 313–4.&lt;/ref&gt; Fellow Whig MPs [[Richard Brinsley Sheridan|Richard Sheridan]] and [[Charles James Fox]] disagreed with Burke and split with him. Fox thought the ''Reflections'' to be &quot;in very bad taste&quot; and &quot;favouring Tory principles&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;L. G. Mitchell, ''Charles James Fox'' (Penguin, 1997), p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt; Other Whigs such as the [[William Cavendish-Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland|Duke of Portland]] and [[William FitzWilliam, 4th Earl FitzWilliam|Earl Fitzwilliam]] privately agreed with Burke but did not wish for a public breach with their Whig colleagues.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke's Reflections'', p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke wrote on 29 November 1790: &quot;I have received from the Duke of Portland, Lord Fitzwilliam, the [[William Cavendish, 5th Duke of Devonshire|Duke of Devonshire]], [[Lord John Cavendish]] [[Frederick Montagu|Montagu]] and a long et cetera of the old Stamina of the Whiggs a most full approbation of the principles of that work and a kind indulgence to the execution&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cobban and Smith (eds.), ''Correspondence of Edmund Burke. Volume VI'', p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt; The Duke of Portland said in 1791 that when anyone criticised the ''Reflections'' to him he informed them that he had recommended the book to his sons as containing the true Whig creed.&lt;ref&gt;Cobban and Smith (eds.), ''Correspondence of Edmund Burke. Volume VI'', p. 161, n. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; In the opinion of [[Paul Langford]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot; /&gt; Burke [[crossing the Rubicon|crossed something of a Rubicon]] when he attended a levee on 3 February 1791 to meet the King, later described by Jane Burke:

&lt;blockquote&gt;On his coming to Town for the Winter, as he generally does, he went to the Levee with the Duke of ''Portland'', who went with [[Lord William Bentinck|Lord William]] to [[Kissing hands|kiss hands]] on his going into the [[Coldstream Guards|Guards]]—while Lord William was kissing hands, The King was talking to The Duke, but his Eyes were fixed on [Burke] who was standing in the Crowd, and when He said His say to The Duke, without waiting for [Burke]'s coming up in his turn, The King went up to him, and, after the usual questions of how long have you been in Town and the weather, He said you have been very much employed of late, and very much confined. [Burke] said, no, Sir, not more than usual—You have and very well employed too, but there are none so deaf as those that w'ont hear, and none so blind as those that w'ont see—[Burke] made a low bow, Sir, I certainly now understand you, but was afraid my vanity or presumption might have led me to imagine what Your Majesty has said referred to what I have done—You cannot be vain—You have been of ''use to us all'', it is a general opinion, is it not so [[John Dalrymple, 6th Earl of Stair|Lord Stair]]? who was standing near. It is said Lord Stair;—Your Majesty's adopting it, Sir, will make the opinion general, said [Burke]—I know it is the general opinion, and I know that there is no Man who calls himself a Gentleman that must not think himself obliged to you, for you have supported the cause of the Gentlemen—You know the tone at Court is a whisper, but The King said all this loud, so as to be heard by every one at Court.&lt;ref&gt;Cobban and Smith (eds.), ''Correspondence of Edmund Burke. Volume VI'', p. 239.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Burke's ''Reflections'' sparked a [[Revolution Controversy|pamphlet war]]. [[Thomas Paine]] penned the ''[[Rights of Man]]'' in 1791 as a response to Burke; [[Mary Wollstonecraft]] published ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Men]]'' and [[James Mackintosh]] wrote ''Vindiciae Gallicae''. Mackintosh was the first to see the ''Reflections'' as &quot;the manifesto of a Counter Revolution&quot;. Mackintosh later agreed with Burke's views, remarking in December 1796 after meeting him, that Burke was &quot;minutely and accurately informed, to a wonderful exactness, with respect to every fact relating to the French Revolution&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; Mackintosh later said: &quot;Burke was one of the first thinkers as well as one of the greatest orators of his time. He is without parallel in any age, excepting perhaps Lord Bacon and Cicero; and his works contain an ampler store of political and moral wisdom than can be found in any other writer whatever&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 491.&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1790, François-Louis-Thibault de Menonville, a member of the National Assembly of France, wrote to Burke, praising the ''Reflections'' and requesting more &quot;very refreshing mental food&quot; that he could publish.&lt;ref&gt;Cobban and Smith (eds.), ''Correspondence of Edmund Burke. Volume VI'', pp. 162–69.&lt;/ref&gt; This Burke did in April 1791 when he published ''A Letter to a Member of the National Assembly''. Burke called for external forces to reverse the Revolution and included an attack on the late French philosopher [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]], as a personality cult had developed in revolutionary France. Although Burke conceded that Rousseau sometimes shows &quot;a considerable insight into human nature&quot; he was mostly critical. Although he did not meet Rousseau on his visit to Britain in 1766–7 he was a friend of [[David Hume]], with whom Rousseau had stayed. Burke said Rousseau &quot;entertained no principle either to influence of his heart, or to guide his understanding, but ''vanity''&quot;, which he &quot;was possessed to a degree little short of madness&quot;. He also cited Rousseau's ''[[Confessions (Jean-Jacques Rousseau)|Confessions]]'' as evidence that Rousseau had a life of &quot;obscure and vulgar vices&quot; that was not &quot;chequered, or spotted here and there, with virtues, or even distinguished by a single good action&quot;. Burke contrasted Rousseau's theory of universal benevolence and his sending his children to a foundling hospital: &quot;a lover of his kind, but a hater of his kindred&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', pp. 356–67.&lt;/ref&gt;

These events and the disagreements that arose from them within the Whig party led to its break-up and to the rupture of Burke's friendship with Fox. In debate in Parliament on Britain's relations with Russia, Fox praised the principles of the Revolution, though Burke was not able to reply at this time as he was &quot;overpowered by continued cries of question from his own side of the House&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 327.&lt;/ref&gt; When Parliament was debating the Quebec Bill for a constitution for Canada, Fox praised the Revolution and criticised some of Burke's arguments, such as hereditary power. On 6 May 1791, during another debate in Parliament on the Quebec Bill, Burke used the opportunity to answer Fox and condemn the new French Constitution and &quot;the horrible consequences flowing from the French idea of the rights of man&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McCue, p. 23&quot;&gt;McCue, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke asserted that those ideas were the antithesis of both the British and the American constitutions.&lt;ref&gt;Frank O'Gorman, ''The Whig Party and the French Revolution'' (Macmillan, 1967), p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke was interrupted, and Fox intervened to say that Burke should be allowed to carry on with his speech. However a vote of censure was moved against Burke for noticing the affairs of France, which was moved by [[John Baker-Holroyd, 1st Earl of Sheffield|Lord Sheffield]] and seconded by Fox.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 328.&lt;/ref&gt; Pitt made a speech praising Burke, and Fox made a speech both rebuking and complimenting Burke. He questioned the sincerity of Burke, who seemed to have forgotten the lessons he had taught him, quoting from Burke's speeches of fourteen and fifteen years before. Burke replied:

[[File:Charles James Fox00.jpg|thumb|left|[[Charles James Fox]].]]
&lt;blockquote&gt;It certainly was indiscreet at any period, but especially at his time of life, to parade enemies, or give his friends occasion to desert him; yet if his firm and steady adherence to the British constitution placed him in such a dilemma, he would risk all, and, as public duty and public experience taught him, with his last words exclaim, &quot;Fly from the French Constitution&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McCue, p. 23&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

At this point, Fox whispered that there was &quot;no loss of friendship&quot;. &quot;I regret to say there is&quot;, Burke said; &quot;I have indeed made a great sacrifice; I have done my duty though I have lost my friend. There is something in the detested French constitution that envenoms every thing it touches&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prior, p. 329&quot;&gt;Prior, p. 329.&lt;/ref&gt; This provoked a reply from Fox, yet he was unable to give his speech for some time since he was overcome with tears and emotion, he appealed to Burke to remember their inalienable friendship but also repeated his criticisms of Burke and uttered &quot;unusually bitter sarcasms&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prior, p. 329&quot; /&gt; This only aggravated the rupture between the two men. Burke demonstrated his separation from the party on 5 June 1791 by writing to Fitzwilliam, declining money from him.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Gorman, p. 75&quot;&gt;O'Gorman, p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke was dismayed that some Whigs, instead of reaffirming the principles of the Whig party he laid out in the ''Reflections'', had rejected them in favour of &quot;French principles&quot; and criticised Burke for abandoning Whig principles. Burke wanted to demonstrate his fidelity to Whig principles and feared that acquiescence to Fox and his followers would allow the Whig party to become a vehicle for Jacobinism. Burke knew that many members of the Whig party did not share Fox's views and wanted to provoke them into condemning the French Revolution. Burke wrote that he wanted to represent the whole Whig party &quot;as tolerating, and by a toleration, countenancing those proceedings&quot; so that he could &quot;stimulate them to a public declaration of what every one of their acquaintance privately knows to be...their sentiments&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;O'Gorman, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore on 3 August 1791 Burke published his ''Appeal from the New to the Old Whigs'', in which he renewed his criticism of the radical revolutionary programmes inspired by the French Revolution and attacked the Whigs who supported them as holding principles contrary to those traditionally held by the Whig party. Burke owned two copies of what has been called &quot;that practical compendium of Whig political theory&quot;, ''The Tryal of Dr. [[Henry Sacheverell]]'' (1710).&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark, p. 40&quot;&gt;Clark, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke wrote of the trial: &quot;It rarely happens to a party to have the opportunity of a clear, authentic, recorded, declaration of their political tenets upon the subject of a great constitutional event like that of the [Glorious] Revolution&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark, p. 40&quot; /&gt; Writing in the third person, Burke asserted in his ''Appeal'':

&lt;blockquote&gt;...that the foundations laid down by the Commons, on the trial of Doctor Sacheverel, for justifying the revolution of 1688, are the very same laid down in Mr. Burke's Reflections; that is to say, —a breach of the ''original contract'', implied and expressed in the constitution of this country, as a scheme of government fundamentally and inviolably fixed in King, Lords and Commons.—That the fundamental subversion of this antient constitution, by one of its parts, having been attempted, and in effect accomplished, justified the Revolution. That it was justified ''only'' upon the ''necessity'' of the case; as the ''only'' means left for the recovery of that ''antient'' constitution, formed by the ''original contract'' of the British state; as well as for the future preservation of the ''same'' government. These are the points to be proved.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark, p. 40&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Burke then provided quotations from Paine's ''Rights of Man'' to demonstrate what the New Whigs believed. Burke's belief that Foxite principles corresponded to Paine's was genuine.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', p. 383.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, Burke denied that a majority of &quot;the people&quot; had, or ought to have, the final say in politics and alter society at their pleasure. People had rights but also duties, and these duties were not voluntary. Also, the people could not overthrow morality derived from God.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', p. 384.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Whig grandees like Portland and Fitzwilliam privately agreed with Burke's ''Appeal'', they wished he had used more moderate language. Fitzwilliam saw the ''Appeal'' as containing &quot;the doctrines I have sworn by, long and long since&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. II, p. 386&quot;&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', p. 386.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Francis Basset, 1st Baron de Dunstanville and Basset|Francis Basset]], a backbench Whig MP, wrote to Burke: &quot;...though for reasons which I will not now detail I did not then deliver my sentiments, I most perfectly differ from Mr Fox &amp; from the great Body of opposition on the French Revolution&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. II, p. 386&quot; /&gt; Burke sent a copy of the ''Appeal'' to the King and the King requested a friend to communicate to Burke that he had read it &quot;with great Satisfaction&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. II, p. 386&quot; /&gt; Burke wrote of its reception: &quot;Not one word from one of our party. They are secretly galled. They agree with me to a title; but they dare not speak out for fear of hurting Fox. ... They leave me to myself; they see that I can do myself justice&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Gorman, p. 75&quot; /&gt; [[Charles Burney]] viewed it as &quot;a most admirable book—the best &amp; most useful on political subjects that I have ever seen&quot; but believed the differences in the Whig party between Burke and Fox should not be publicly aired.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', pp. 385–6.&lt;/ref&gt;

Eventually most of the Whigs sided with Burke and gave their support to Pitt's conservative government, which, in response to France's declaration of war against Britain, declared war on France's revolutionary government in 1793.

In December 1791, Burke sent government ministers his ''Thoughts on French Affairs'' where he put forward three main points: no counter-revolution in France would come about by purely domestic causes; the longer the revolutionary government exists the stronger it becomes; and the revolutionary government's interest and aim is to disturb all the other governments of Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, pp. 357–8.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke, as a Whig, did not wish to see an absolute monarchy again in France after the extirpation of Jacobinism. Writing to an ''émigré'' in 1791, Burke expressed his views against a restoration of the ''ancien régime'':

&lt;blockquote&gt;When such a complete convulsion has shaken the State, and hardly left any thing whatsoever, either in civil arrangements, or in the Characters and disposition of men's minds, exactly where it was, whatever shall be settled although in the former persons and upon old forms, will be in some measure a new thing and will labour under something of the weakness as well as other inconveniences of a Change. My poor opinion is that you mean to establish what you call 'L'ancien Regime,' If any one means that system of Court Intrigue miscalled a Government as it stood, at Versailles before the present confusions as the thing to be established, that I believe will be found absolutely impossible; and if you consider the Nature, as well of persons, as of affairs, I flatter myself you must be of my opinion. That was tho' not so violent a State of Anarchy as well as the present. If it were even possible to lay things down exactly as they stood, before the series of experimental politicks began, I am quite sure that they could not long continue in that situation. In one Sense of L'Ancien Regime I am clear that nothing else can reasonably be done.&lt;ref&gt;Cobban and Smith (eds.), ''Correspondence of Edmund Burke. Volume VI'', pp. 479–80.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Burke delivered a speech on the debate of the [[Aliens Act 1793|Aliens Bill]] on 28 December 1792. He supported the Bill as it would exclude &quot;murderous atheists, who would pull down church and state; religion and God; morality and happiness&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. II, p. 439&quot;&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', p. 439.&lt;/ref&gt; The peroration included a reference to a French order for 3,000 daggers. Burke revealed a dagger he had concealed in his coat and threw it to the floor: &quot;This is what you are to gain by an alliance with France&quot;. Burke picked up the dagger and continued:

&lt;blockquote&gt;When they smile, I see blood trickling down their faces; I see their insidious purposes; I see that the object of all their cajoling is—blood! I now warn my countrymen to beware of these execrable philosophers, whose only object it is to destroy every thing that is good here, and to establish immorality and murder by precept and example—'Hic niger est hunc tu Romane caveto' ['Such a man is evil; beware of him, Roman'. Horace, ''Satires'' I. 4. 85.].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. II, p. 439&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Burke supported the war against revolutionary France, seeing Britain as fighting on the side of the royalists and ''émigres'' in a civil war, rather than fighting against the whole nation of France.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. II, p. 453&quot;&gt;Lock, ''Burke. Vol. II'', p. 453.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke also supported the [[War in the Vendée|royalist uprising]] in [[Vendée|La Vendée]], describing it on 4 November 1793 in a letter to [[William Windham]], as &quot;the sole affair I have much heart in&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, Burke. Vol. II, p. 453&quot; /&gt; Burke wrote to [[Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville|Henry Dundas]] on 7 October urging him to send reinforcements there, as he viewed it as the only theatre in the war that might lead to a march on Paris. However Dundas did not follow Burke's advice. Burke believed the government was not taking the uprising seriously enough, a view reinforced by a letter he had received from the [[Charles X of France|Comte d'Artois]], dated 23 October, requesting that he intercede on behalf of the royalists to the government. Burke was forced to reply on 6 November: &quot;I am not in His Majesty's Service; or at all consulted in his Affairs&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;O'Gorman, pp. 168–69.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke published his ''Remarks on the Policy of the Allies with Respect to France'', begun in October, where he said: &quot;I am sure every thing has shewn us that in this war with France, one Frenchman is worth twenty foreigners. La Vendee is a proof of this&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Edmund Burke, ''The Works of the Right Honourable Edmund Burke. Volume VII'' (F. C. and J. Rivington, 1815), p. 141.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20 June 1794, Burke received a vote of thanks from the Commons for his services in the Hastings trial and immediately resigned his seat, being replaced by his son Richard. However a terrible blow fell upon Burke in the loss of Richard in August 1794, to whom he was tenderly attached, and in whom he saw signs of promise,&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot; /&gt; which were not patent to others, and which in fact appear to have been non-existent. The King, whose favour he had gained by his attitude on the French Revolution, wished to make him [[Earl of Beaconsfield|Lord Beaconsfield]], but the death of his son had deprived such an honour of all its attractions, and the only reward he would accept was a pension of £2,500. Even this modest reward was attacked by the [[John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford|Duke of Bedford]] and the [[James Maitland, 8th Earl of Lauderdale|Earl of Lauderdale]], to whom Burke replied in the ''Letter to a Noble Lord'' (1796).&lt;ref&gt;Prior, pp. 425–6.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke wrote: &quot;It cannot at this time be too often repeated; line upon line; precept upon precept; until it comes into the currency of a proverb, ''To innovate is not to reform''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Edmund Burke, ''A Letter from The Right Honourable Edmund Burke to a Noble Lord, on the Attacks made upon him and his pension, in the House of Lords, by The Duke of Bedford and The Earl of Lauderdale, Early in the present Sessions of Parliament.'' (F. and C. Rivington, 1796), p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; He argued that he was rewarded on merit but the Duke of Bedford received his rewards from inheritance alone, his ancestor being the original pensioner: &quot;Mine was from a mild and benevolent sovereign; his from Henry the Eighth&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Burke, ''A Letter to a Noble Lord'', p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke also hinted at what would happen to such people if their revolutionary ideas were implemented, and included a description of the British constitution:

&lt;blockquote&gt;But as to ''our'' country and ''our'' race, as long as the well compacted structure of our church and state, the sanctuary, the holy of holies of that ancient law, defended by reverence, defended by power, a fortress at once and a temple, shall stand inviolate on the brow of the British Sion—as long as the British Monarchy, not more limited than fenced by the orders of the State, shall, like the proud Keep of Windsor, rising in the majesty of proportion, and girt with the double belt of its kindred and coeval towers, as long as this awful structure shall oversee and guard the subjected land—so long as the mounds and dykes of the low, fat, Bedford level will have nothing to fear from all the pickaxes of all the levellers of France.&lt;ref&gt;Burke, ''A Letter to a Noble Lord'', pp. 52–53.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Burke's last publications were the ''[[Letters on a Regicide Peace]]'' (October 1796), called forth by the Pitt government's negotiations for peace with France. Burke regarded this as appeasement, injurious to national dignity and honour.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, pp. 439–40.&lt;/ref&gt; In the Second Letter, Burke wrote of the revolutionary French government: &quot;Individuality is left out of their scheme of government. The state is all in all. Everything is referred to the production of force; afterwards, everything is trusted to the use of it. It is military in its principle, in its maxims, in its spirit, and in all its movements. The state has dominion and conquest for its sole objects—dominion over minds by proselytism, over bodies by arms&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Steven Blakemore, 'Burke and the Revolution: Bicentennial Reflections', in Blakemore (ed.), ''Burke and the French Revolution. Bicentennial Essays'' (The [[University of Georgia Press]], 1992), p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt; This has been seen as the first time someone explained the modern [[totalitarianism|totalitarian]] state.&lt;ref&gt;Blakemore, p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke regarded the war with France as ideological, against an &quot;armed doctrine&quot;. He wished that France would not be partitioned due to the effect this would have on the balance of power in Europe, and that the war was not against France but against the revolutionaries governing her.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, pp. 443–4.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke said: &quot;It is not France extending a foreign empire over other nations: it is a sect aiming at universal empire, and beginning with the conquest of France&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot; /&gt;

== Later life ==
In November 1795, there was a debate in Parliament on the high price of corn and Burke wrote a memorandum to Pitt on the subject. In December [[Samuel Whitbread (1764–1815)|Samuel Whitbread]] MP introduced a bill giving magistrates the power to fix minimum wages and Fox said he would vote for it. This debate probably led Burke to editing his memorandum as there appeared a notice that Burke would soon publish a letter on the subject to the Secretary of the Board of Agriculture ([[Arthur Young (writer)|Arthur Young]]), but he failed to complete it. These fragments were inserted into the memorandum after his death and published posthumously in 1800 as ''[[Thoughts and Details on Scarcity]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Eccleshall, ''English Conservatism since the Restoration'' (London: Unwin Hyman, 1990), p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; In it, Burke expounded &quot;some of the doctrines of political economists bearing upon agriculture as a trade&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 419.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke criticised policies such as maximum prices and state regulation of wages, and set out what the limits of government should be:

&lt;blockquote&gt;That the State ought to confine itself to what regards the State, or the creatures of the State, namely, the exterior establishment of its religion; its magistracy; its revenue; its military force by sea and land; the corporations that owe their existence to its fiat; in a word, to every thing that is ''truly and properly'' public, to the public peace, to the public safety, to the public order, to the public prosperity.&lt;ref&gt;Eccleshall, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The economist [[Adam Smith]] remarked that Burke was &quot;the only man I ever knew who thinks on economic subjects exactly as I do, without any previous communications having passed between us&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;E. G. West, ''Adam Smith'' (New York: Arlington House, 1969), p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt;

Writing to a friend in May 1795, Burke surveyed the causes of discontent: &quot;I think I can hardly overrate the malignity of the principles of Protestant ascendency, as they affect Ireland; or of Indianism [i.e. corporate tyranny, as practiced by the British East Indies Company], as they affect these countries, and as they affect Asia; or of Jacobinism, as they affect all Europe, and the state of human society itself. The last is the greatest evil&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;R. B. McDowell (ed.), ''The Correspondence of Edmund Burke. Volume VIII'' (Cambridge University Press, 1969), p. 254.&lt;/ref&gt; However by March 1796 Burke had changed his mind: &quot;Our Government and our Laws are beset by two different Enemies, which are sapping its foundations, Indianism, and Jacobinism. In some Cases they act separately, in some they act in conjunction: But of this I am sure; that the first is the worst by far, and the hardest to deal with; and for this amongst other reasons, that it weakens discredits, and ruins that force, which ought to be employed with the greatest Credit and Energy against the other; and that it furnishes Jacobinism with its strongest arms against all ''formal'' Government&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McDowell (ed.), ''Correspondence of Edmund Burke. Volume VIII'', p. 432.&lt;/ref&gt;

For more than a year before his death, Burke knew that his stomach was &quot;irrecoverably ruind&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot; /&gt; After hearing that Burke was nearing death, Fox wrote to Mrs. Burke enquiring after him. Fox received the reply the next day:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Mrs. Burke presents her compliments to Mr. Fox, and thanks him for his obliging inquiries. Mrs. Burke communicated his letter to Mr. Burke, and by his desire has to inform Mr. Fox that it has cost Mr. Burke the most heart-felt pain to obey the stern voice of his duty in rending asunder a long friendship, but that he deemed this sacrifice necessary; that his principles continue the same; and that in whatever of life may yet remain to him, he conceives that he must live for others and not for himself. Mr. Burke is convinced that the principles which he has endeavoured to maintain are necessary to the welfare and dignity of his country, and that these principles can be enforced only by the general persuasion of his sincerity.&lt;ref&gt;Prior, p. 456&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Burke died in [[Beaconsfield]], Buckinghamshire, on 9 July 1797 and was buried there alongside his son and brother. His wife survived him by nearly fifteen years.

== Legacy ==
{{Conservatism sidebar |People}}
[[File:Edmund Burke statue by Matthew Bisanz.JPG|thumb|[[Edmund Burke (Thomas)|Statue of Edmund Burke]] in Washington, D.C.]]

Burke is regarded by most political historians in the English-speaking world as the father of modern English conservatism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dehsen1999&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Christian D. Von Dehsen|title=Philosophers and Religious Leaders|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=25yC2ePhbXEC&amp;pg=PA36|accessdate=1 March 2013|date=21 October 1999|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-1-57356-152-5|pages=36–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eccleshall1990&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Robert Eccleshall|title=English Conservatism Since the Restoration: An Introduction &amp; Anthology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=QfX97Gj9x2sC&amp;pg=PA39|accessdate=1 March 2013|year=1990|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-04-445773-2|pages=39–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dobson2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Andrew Dobson|title=An Introduction to the Politics and Philosophy of José Ortega Y Gasset|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=L4jUNu15kyEC&amp;pg=PA73|accessdate=1 March 2013|date=19 November 2009|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-12331-0|pages=73–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Burke was utilitarian and empirical in his arguments, while [[Joseph de Maistre]], a fellow conservative from the continent, was more a providentialist and sociological and used a more confrontational tone in his arguments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lebrun2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Richard Lebrun|title=Joseph de Maistre's Life, Thought, and Influence: Selected Studies|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=JB7y_ARSN6YC&amp;pg=PA164|accessdate=1 March 2013|date=8 October 2001|publisher=McGill-Queen's Press – MQUP|isbn=978-0-7735-2288-6|pages=164–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke's ideas placing property at the base of human development and the development of society were radical and new at the time.{{citation needed|date=December 2013}} Burke believed that property was essential to human life. Because of his conviction that people desire to be ruled and controlled, the division of property formed the basis for social structure, helping develop control within a property-based hierarchy. He viewed the social changes brought on by property as the natural order of events that should be taking place as the human race progressed. With the division of property and the class system, he also believed that it kept the monarch in check to the needs of the classes beneath the monarch. Since property largely aligned or defined divisions of social class, class too was seen as natural—part of a social agreement that the setting of persons into different classes is the mutual benefit of all subjects.

Burke's support for Irish Catholics and Indians often led him to be criticised by [[Tory (British political party)|Tories]].&lt;ref&gt;J. J. Sack, ''From Jacobite to Conservative. Reaction and orthodoxy in Britain, c. 1760 – 1832'' (Cambridge University Press, 2004), p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt; His opposition to British imperialism in Ireland and India and his opposition to French imperialism and radicalism in Europe, made it difficult for Whig or Tory to accept Burke wholly as their own.&lt;ref&gt;Sack, p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 19th century Burke was praised by both liberals and conservatives. Burke's friend Philip Francis wrote that Burke &quot;was a man who truly &amp; prophetically foresaw all the consequences which would rise from the adoption of the French principles&quot; but because Burke wrote with so much passion people were doubtful of his arguments.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory Claeys, 'The ''Reflections'' refracted: the critical reception of Burke's ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'' during the early 1790s', in John Whale (ed.), ''Edmund Burke's Reflections on the Revolution in France. New interdisciplinary essays'' ([[Manchester University Press]], 2000), p. 55, n. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; William Windham spoke from the same bench in the House of Commons as Burke had done when he had separated from Fox and an observer said Windham spoke &quot;like the ghost of Burke&quot; when he made a speech against peace with France in 1801.&lt;ref&gt;A. D. Harvey, ''Britain in the early nineteenth century'' (B T Batsford Ltd, 1978), p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Hazlitt]], a political opponent of Burke, regarded him as amongst his three favourite writers (the others being Junius and Rousseau), and made it &quot;a test of the sense and candour of any one belonging to the opposite party, whether he allowed Burke to be a great man&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke's Reflections'', p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Wordsworth]] was originally a supporter of the French Revolution and attacked Burke in 'A Letter to the Bishop of Llandaff' (1793) but by the early 19th century he had changed his mind and came to admire Burke. In his ''Two Addresses to the Freeholders of Westmorland'' Wordsworth called Burke &quot;the most sagacious Politician of his age&quot; whose predictions &quot;time has verified&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, p. 173&quot;&gt;Lock, ''Burke's Reflections'', p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt; He later revised his poem ''[[The Prelude]]'' to include praise of Burke (&quot;Genius of Burke! forgive the pen seduced/By specious wonders&quot;) and portrayed him as an old oak.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lock, p. 173&quot; /&gt; [[Samuel Taylor Coleridge]] came to have a similar conversion: he had criticised Burke in ''[[The Watchman (periodical)|The Watchman]]'' but in his ''Friend'' (1809–10) Coleridge defended Burke from charges of inconsistency.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke's Reflections'', pp. 173–4.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in his ''[[Biographia Literaria]]'' (1817) Coleridge hails Burke as a prophet and praises Burke for referring &quot;habitually to ''principles''. He was a ''scientific'' statesman; and therefore a ''seer''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lock, ''Burke's Reflections'', p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Henry Brougham, 1st Baron Brougham and Vaux|Henry Brougham]] wrote of Burke: &quot;... all his predictions, save one momentary expression, had been more than fulfilled: anarchy and bloodshed had borne sway in France; conquest and convulsion had desolated Europe...the providence of mortals is not often able to penetrate so far as this into futurity&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Claeys, p. 50&quot;&gt;Claeys, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; [[George Canning]] believed that Burke's ''Reflections'' &quot;has been justified by the course of subsequent events; and almost every prophecy has been strictly fulfilled&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Claeys, p. 50&quot; /&gt; In 1823 Canning wrote that he took Burke's &quot;last works and words [as] the manual of my politics&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;E. J. Stapleton (ed.), ''Some Official Correspondence of George Canning. Volume I'' (London: Longmans, Green &amp; Co., 1887), p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; The Conservative Prime Minister [[Benjamin Disraeli]] &quot;was deeply penetrated with the spirit and sentiment of Burke's later writings&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;William Flavelle Monypenny and George Earle Buckle, ''The Life of Benjamin Disraeli. Earl of Beaconsfield. Volume I. 1804–1859'' (London: John Murray, 1929), p. 310.&lt;/ref&gt; The Liberal Prime Minister [[William Ewart Gladstone]] considered Burke &quot;a magazine of wisdom on Ireland and America&quot; and in his diary recorded: &quot;Made many extracts from Burke—''sometimes almost divine''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;John Morley, ''The Life of William Ewart Gladstone. Volume III (1880–1898)'' (London: Macmillan, 1903), p. 280.&lt;/ref&gt; The Radical MP and anti-[[Corn Law]] activist [[Richard Cobden]] often praised Burke's ''Thoughts and Details on Scarcity''.&lt;ref&gt;John Morley, ''The Life of Richard Cobden'' (London: T. Fisher Unwin, 1905), p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt; The Liberal historian [[John Dalberg-Acton, 1st Baron Acton|Lord Acton]] considered Burke one of the three greatest liberals, along with William Gladstone and [[Thomas Babington Macaulay, 1st Baron Macaulay|Thomas Babington Macaulay]].&lt;ref&gt;Herbert Paul (ed.), ''Letters of Lord Acton to Mary Gladstone'' (Macmillan, 1914), p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; Macaulay recorded in his diary: &quot;I have now finished reading again most of Burke's works. Admirable! The greatest man since [[John Milton|Milton]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sir George Trevelyan, ''The Life and Letters of Lord Macaulay. Volume II'' (London: Longmans, 1876), p. 377.&lt;/ref&gt; The Gladstonian Liberal MP [[John Morley]] published two books on Burke (including a biography) and was influenced by Burke, including his views on prejudice.&lt;ref&gt;D. A. Hamer, ''John Morley. Liberal Intellectual in Politics'' (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1968), p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt; The Cobdenite Radical [[Francis Wrigley Hirst|Francis Hirst]] thought Burke deserved &quot;a place among English libertarians, even though of all lovers of liberty and of all reformers he was the most conservative, the least abstract, always anxious to preserve and renovate rather than to innovate. In politics he resembled the modern architect who would restore an old house instead of pulling it down to construct a new one on the site&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;F. W. Hirst, ''Liberty and Tyranny'' (London: Duckworth, 1935), pp. 105–6.&lt;/ref&gt; Burke's ''[[Reflections on the Revolution in France]]'' was controversial at the time of its publication, but after his death, it was to become his best-known and most influential work, and a manifesto of conservative thought.

Two contrasting assessments of Burke were offered long after his death by [[Karl Marx]] and [[Winston Churchill]]. In ''[[Das Kapital]]'', Marx wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The sycophant—who in the pay of the English oligarchy played the romantic ''laudator temporis acti'' against the French Revolution just as, in the pay of the North American colonies at the beginning of the American troubles, he had played the liberal against the English oligarchy—was an out-and-out vulgar [[bourgeois]]. &quot;The laws of commerce are the laws of Nature, and therefore the laws of God.&quot; (E. Burke, l.c., pp. 31, 32) No wonder that, true to the laws of God and Nature, he always sold himself in the best market.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Winston Churchill, in &quot;Consistency in Politics&quot;, wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
On the one hand [Burke] is revealed as a foremost apostle of Liberty, on the other as the redoubtable champion of Authority. But a charge of political inconsistency applied to this life appears a mean and petty thing. History easily discerns the reasons and forces which actuated him, and the immense changes in the problems he was facing which evoked from the same profound mind and sincere spirit these entirely contrary manifestations. His soul revolted against tyranny, whether it appeared in the aspect of a domineering Monarch and a corrupt Court and Parliamentary system, or whether, mouthing the watch-words of a non-existent liberty, it towered up against him in the dictation of a brutal mob and wicked sect. No one can read the Burke of Liberty and the Burke of Authority without feeling that here was the same man pursuing the same ends, seeking the same ideals of society and Government, and defending them from assaults, now from one extreme, now from the other.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The historian [[Piers Brendon]] asserts that Burke laid the moral foundations for the [[British Empire]], epitomised in the trial of [[Warren Hastings]], that was ultimately to be its undoing: when Burke stated that &quot;The British Empire must be governed on a plan of freedom, for it will be governed by no other&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;K. Brittlebank, ''Tipu Sultan's Search for Legitimacy'' (Delhi, 1997), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; this was &quot;...an ideological bacillus that would prove fatal. This was Edmund Burke's paternalistic doctrine that colonial government was a trust. It was to be so exercised for the benefit of subject people that they would eventually attain their birthright—freedom&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Brendon, p. xviii.&lt;/ref&gt; As a consequence of this opinion, Burke objected to the opium trade, which he called a &quot;smuggling adventure&quot; and condemned &quot;the great Disgrace of the British character in India&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;F. G. Whelan, ''Edmund Burke and India'' (Pittsburgh, 1996), p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Royal Society of Arts]] [[blue plaque]] commemorates Burke at 37 Gerrard Street in [[Chinatown, London|London's Chinatown]].&lt;ref name='EngHet'&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/discover/blue-plaques/search/burke-edmund-1729-1797|title=BURKE, EDMUND (1729–1797)|publisher=English Heritage| accessdate=23 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious thought of Edmund Burke==
{{main|religious thought of Edmund Burke}}
The religious thought of Edmund Burke includes published works by [[Edmund Burke]] and commentary on the same. Burke's religious thought was grounded in his belief that religion is the foundation of civil society.&lt;ref&gt;Edmund Burke, ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'' (London: J. M. Dent &amp; Sons, 1964), 87.&lt;/ref&gt;  He sharply criticized deism and atheism, and emphasized Christianity as a vehicle of social progress. &lt;ref&gt;Ian Harris, “Burke and Religion,” in David Dwan and Christopher J Insole eds., ''The Cambridge Companion to Edmund Burke'' (Cambridge University Press, 2012), 103.&lt;/ref&gt;  Born in Ireland to a Protestant father and Catholic mother, Burke vigorously defended the Church of England but also demonstrated sensitivity to Catholic concerns. &lt;ref name=&quot;Ibid&quot; /&gt;  He linked the conservation of a state religion with the preservation of citizens’ constitutional liberties and highlighted Christianity’s benefits not only to the believer’s soul but also to political arrangements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ibid&quot;&gt;Harris, 98.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Famous quotes===
The statement that &quot;The only thing necessary for the triumph of evil is for good men to do nothing&quot; is often attributed to Burke. Although it has not been found in his speeches, writings, or letters (and is thus apocryphal), in 1770 he wrote in ''[[Thoughts on the Cause of the Present Discontents]]'' that &quot;when bad men combine, the good must associate; else they will fall, one by one, an unpitied sacrifice in a contemptible struggle.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=BrGAIvlkf-sC&amp;pg=PR13 |date=1 January 1990 |title=Edmund Burke: appraisals and applications |isbn=978-0-88738-328-1 |author=Daniel Ritchie}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=kbouAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA106| title=Thoughts on the cause of the present discontents |year=1770 |author=Edmund Burke}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Stuart Mill]] made a similar statement in an inaugural address delivered to the University of St. Andrews in 1867: &quot;Bad men need nothing more to compass their ends, than that good men should look on and do nothing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=DFNAAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq=%22Bad+men+need+nothing+more+to+compass+their+ends,+than+that+good+men+should+look+on+and+do+nothing%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=RUh5U6qWBLSysQT0vYGAAw&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Bad%20men%20need%20nothing%20more%20to%20compass%20their%20ends%2C%20than%20that%20good%20men%20should%20look%20on%20and%20do%20nothing%22&amp;f=false ''Inaugural Address Delivered to the University of St. Andrews, Feb. 1st 1867'' (1867)], p. 36&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke is sometimes credited with the line, &quot;Those who don't know history are doomed to repeat it.&quot; It does not appear in reliable sources.&lt;ref&gt;It is not among the 67 authentic Burke quotes in John Bartlett, ''Bartlett's Familiar Quotations: A Collection of Passages, Phrases, and Proverbs Traced to Their Sources in Ancient and Modern Literature'' (16th ed. 1992), pp 330-32&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bibliography ==
* ''Vindication of Natural Society'' (1756)
* ''A Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful'' (1756)
* ''An Account of the European Settlement in America'' (1757)
* ''The Abridgement of the History of England'' (1757)
* ''Annual Register'' editor for some 30 years (1758)
* ''Tracts on the Popery Laws'' (Early 1760's)
* ''On the Present State of the Nation'' (1769)
* ''Thoughts on the Cause of the Present Discontents'' (1770)
* ''American Taxation'' (1774)
* ''Conciliation with the Colonies'' (1775)
* ''A Letter to the Sheriffs of Bristol'' (1777)
* ''Reform of the Representation in the House of Commons'' (1782)
* ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'' (1790)
* ''Letter to a Member of the National Assembly'' (1791)
* ''Appeal from the New to the Old Whigs'' (1791)
* ''Thoughts on French Affairs'' (1791)
* ''Remarks on the Policy of the Allies'' (1793)
* ''Letters on a Regicide Peace'' (1795–97)
* ''Letter to a Noble Lord'' (1796)

== Timeline ==
&lt;timeline&gt;
ImageSize = width:450 height:500
PlotArea = left:50 right:0 bottom:10 top:10

DateFormat = yyyy
Period = from:1725 till:1800
TimeAxis = orientation:vertical
ScaleMajor = unit:year increment:5 start:1725
ScaleMinor = unit:year increment:1 start:1725

PlotData =
  color: red mark:(line,black) align: left fontsize:S
  shift:(25,0) # shift text to right side of bar

  # there is no automatic collision detection, fontsize:XS
  # so shift texts up or down manually to avoid overlap shift:(25,-10)

  at:1729 text:(1729) Born in Dublin
  at:1743 text:(1743) Enters Trinity College
  at:1750 text:Enters Middle Temple
  at:1756 text:Publishes treatise On the Sublime and Beautiful
  at:1765 shift:(15,-5) text:Employed as Secretary to Rockingham
  at:1766 text:Enters House of Commons
  at:1775 text:Delivers on Conciliation with America
  at:1782 text:Paymaster of Forces and P.C.; ~ joined coalition of Fox and North
  from:1787 till:1794 shift:(25,6) text:Leads in prosecution of W. Hastings
  at:1790 text:Publishes Reflections on French Revolution; ~ breaks with Fox party
  at:1794 text:Retires from House of Commons
  at:1796 text:Publishes Letter on a Regicide Peace
  at:1797 shift:(25,5) text:Dies
&lt;/timeline&gt;

== Notes ==
{{reflist|25em}}

== References ==
{{refbegin|30em}}
*{{A Short Biographical Dictionary of English Literature}}
*Blakemore, Steven (ed.), ''Burke and the French Revolution. Bicentennial Essays'' (The University of Georgia Press, 1992).
*[[David Bromwich|Bromwich, David]], ''The Intellectual Life of Edmund Burke: From the Sublime and Beautiful to American Independence'' (Cambridge, MA: [[Belknap Press]], 2014). A review: ''[http://www.economist.com/news/books-and-arts/21606252-ideal-political-role-model-freedom-fighter Freedom fighter]'', The Economist, July 5, 2014
*Cone, Carl B. ''Burke and the Nature of Politics (2 vols, 1957, 1964), a detailed modern biography of Burke; somewhat uncritical and sometimes superficial regarding politics
*Thomas Wellsted Copeland, 'Edmund Burke and the Book Reviews in Dodsley's Annual Register', ''Publications of the Modern Language Association'', Vol. 57, No. 2. (Jun. 1942), pp.&amp;nbsp;446–468.
*Courtenay, C.P. ''Montesquieu and Burke'' (1963), good introduction
*Crowe, Ian, ed. ''The Enduring Edmund Burke: Bicentennial Essays'' (1997) essays by American conservatives [http://www.questia.com/read/82425344?title=The%20Enduring%20Edmund%20Burke%3a%20Bicentennial%20Essays online edition]
*Crowe, Ian, ed. ''An Imaginative Whig: Reassessing the Life and Thought of Edmund Burke.'' (2005). 247 pp. essays by scholars
*Ian Crowe, 'The career and political thought of Edmund Burke', ''Journal of Liberal History'', Issue 40, Autumn 2003.
*Frederick Dreyer, 'The Genesis of Burke's Reflections', ''The Journal of Modern History'', Vol. 50, No. 3. (Sep. 1978), pp.&amp;nbsp;462–479.
*Robert Eccleshall, ''English Conservatism since the Restoration'' (London: Unwin Hyman, 1990).
*Gibbons, Luke. ''Edmund Burke and Ireland: Aesthetics, Politics, and the Colonial Sublime.'' (2003). 304 pp.
*{{Cite book| publisher=Dorset Press | isbn = 0-88029-399-3 | last = Hibbert | first = Christopher | title = King Mob: The Story of Lord George Gordon and the Riots of 1780 | date = May 1990 }}
*[[Russell Kirk]], ''The Conservative Mind: From Burke to Eliot'' (7th ed. 1992).
*Kirk, Russell. ''Edmund Burke: A Genius Reconsidered'' (1997) by a leader of [[Conservatism in the United States|American conservatism]] [http://www.questia.com/read/85677594?title=Edmund%20Burke%3a%20A%20Genius%20Reconsidered online edition]
*Kramnick, Isaac. ''The Rage of Edmund Burke: Portrait of an Ambivalent Conservative'' (1977) [http://www.questia.com/read/100291647?title=The%20Rage%20of%20Edmund%20Burke%3a%20Portrait%20of%20an%20Ambivalent%20Conservative online edition]
*Lock, F. P. ''Burke's Reflections on the Revolution in France'' (London: Allen &amp; Unwin, 1985).
*Lock, F. P. ''Edmund Burke. Volume I: 1730–1784'' (Clarendon Press, 1999).
*Lock, F. P. ''Edmund Burke. Volume II: 1784–1797'' (Clarendon Press, 2006).
*Levin, Yuval. ''The Great Debate: Edmund Burke, Thomas Paine, and the Birth of Right and Left'' (Basic Books; 2013) 275 pages; their debate over the French Revolution.
*Lucas, Paul. &quot;On Edmund Burke's Doctrine of Prescription; Or, An Appeal from the New to the Old Lawyers&quot;, ''Historical Journal,'' 11 (1968) opens the way towards an effective synthesis of Burke's ideas of History, Change and Prescription.
*Jim McCue, ''Edmund Burke and Our Present Discontents'' (The Claridge Press, 1997).
*Magnus, Philip. ''Edmund Burke: A Life'' (1939), older biography
*Marshall, P. J. ''The Impeachment of Warren Hastings'' (1965), the standard history of the trial and Burke's role
*[[Conor Cruise O'Brien]], ''The Great Melody. A Thematic Biography of Edmund Burke'' (1992). ISBN 0-226-61651-7.
*O'Gorman, Frank. ''Edmund Burke: Edmund Burke: His Political Philosophy'' (2004) 153pp [http://www.questia.com/read/108557108?title=Political%20Thinkers%3a%20%20Edmund%20Burke online edition]
*Parkin, Charles. ''The Moral Basis of Burke's Political Thought'' (1956)
*Pocock, J.G.A. &quot;Burke and the Ancient Constitution&quot;, ''Historical Journal,'' 3 (1960), 125–43; shows Burke's debt to the Common Law tradition of the 17th century [http://www.jstor.org/pss/3020472 in JSTOR]
*Raeder, Linda C. &quot;Edmund Burke: Old Whig&quot;. ''Political Science Reviewer'' 2006 35: 115–131. Issn: 0091-3715 Fulltext: [[Ebsco]], argues Burke's ideas closely resemble those of conservative philosopher [[Friedrich August von Hayek]] (1899–1992).
*J. J. Sack, 'The Memory of Burke and the Memory of Pitt: English Conservatism Confronts Its Past, 1806–1829', ''[[The Historical Journal]]'', Vol. 30, No. 3. (Sep. 1987), pp.&amp;nbsp;623–640.
*J. J. Sack, ''From Jacobite to Conservative. Reaction and orthodoxy in Britain, c. 1760 – 1832'' (Cambridge University Press, 2004).
*Spinner, Jeff. &quot;Constructing Communities: Edmund Burke on Revolution&quot;, ''Polity,'' Vol. 23, No. 3 (Spring, 1991), pp.&amp;nbsp;395–421 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3235133 in JSTOR]
*Stanlis, Peter. ''Edmund Burke and the Natural Law'' (1958)
*Vermeir, Koen and Funk Deckard, Michael (ed.) ''The Science of Sensibility: Reading Burke's Philosophical Enquiry'' (International Archives of the History of Ideas, Vol. 206) (Springer, 2012)
*John Whale (ed.), ''Edmund Burke's Reflections on the Revolution in France. New interdisciplinary essays'' (Manchester University Press, 2000).
*Whelan, Frederick G. ''Edmund Burke and India: Political Morality and Empire'' (1996)
*O'Connor Power, J. 'Edmund Burke and His Abiding Influence', ''The North'' ''American Review'', vol. 165 issue 493, December 1897, 666–81.
{{refend}}

===Primary sources===
*[[J. C. D. Clark]] (ed.), ''Reflections on the Revolution in France. A Critical Edition'' (Stanford University Press, 2001).
*''Burke's Politics'' (1949), edited by R. Hoffman and P. Levack
*Burke, Edmund, ''The Writings and Speeches of Edmund Burke'' (9 vol 1981– ) [http://www.questia.com/read/59629780?title=The%20Writings%20and%20Speeches%20of%20Edmund%20Burke%20-%20Vol.%201 vol 1 online]; [http://www.questia.com/read/73877114?title=The%20Writings%20and%20Speeches%20of%20Edmund%20Burke%20-%20Vol.%202 vol 2 online]; [http://www.questia.com/read/73877114?title=The%20Writings%20and%20Speeches%20of%20Edmund%20Burke%20-%20Vol.%202 vol 6 ''India: The Launching of the Hastings Impeachment, 1786–1788'' online]; [http://www.questia.com/read/74655036?title=The%20Writings%20and%20Speeches%20of%20Edmund%20Burke%20-%20Vol.%208 vol 8 online]; [http://www.questia.com/read/29059987?title=The%20Writings%20and%20Speeches%20of%20Edmund%20Burke%20-%20Vol.%209 vol 9 online];

== External links ==
{{Sister project links|s=Author:Edmund Burke|wikt=no|v=no|b=no|n=no}}
*[http://www.wikicu.com/Edmund_Burke_Society Edmund Burke Society at Columbia University]
*{{sep entry|burke|Edmund Burke|Ian Harris}}
*[http://www.fundacionburke.org Spanish foundation based on Burke's thoughts]
*[http://www.gettysburg.edu/special_collections/collections/manuscripts/collections/ms016.dot Edmund Burke Papers at Gettysburg College]
*[http://oll.libertyfund.org/index.php?option=com_staticxt&amp;staticfile=show.php%3Fperson=3807&amp;Itemid=28 Burke's works at The Online Library of Liberty]
*{{gutenberg author|id=Edmund+Burke | name=Edmund Burke}} (including his collected works in twelve volumes)
*{{Worldcat id|lccn-n79-40055}}
*{{In Our Time|Edmund Burke|b00sjqyn|Edmund_Burke}}
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/burke_edmund.shtml BBC – History – Edmund Burke]
*{{dmoz|Science/Social_Sciences/Political_Science/Political_Philosophy/Political_Philosophers/Burke, _Edmund}}
*[http://www.berfrois.com/2011/06/burkes-wardrobe-william-f-byrne/ &quot;Edmund Burke for a Postmodern Age&quot;], William F. Byrne, ''[http://www.berfrois.com/ Berfrois]'', 29 June 2011
*[https://archive.org/details/ANOPPORTUNITYFORPEACEExcerptsFromEdmundBurkesOnConciliation1775_201302 &quot;AN OPPORTUNITY FOR PEACE: Excerpts from Edmund Burke’s 'On Conciliation' (1775)&quot;]
*{{NRA|id=P4213}}
*{{npg name|id=00648|name=Edmund Burke}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Richard Rigby]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Paymaster of the Forces]]|years=1782}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Isaac Barré]]}}
{{s-bef|before=Isaac Barré}}
{{s-ttl|title=Paymaster of the Forces|years=1783–1784}}
{{s-aft|after=[[William Wyndham Grenville, 1st Baron Grenville|William Wyndham Grenville]]}}
{{S-par|gb}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Richard Chandler-Cavendish]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Verney Lovett]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Wendover (UK Parliament constituency)|Member of Parliament for Wendover]]|years=1765–1774}}
{{s-aft|after= [[Joseph Bullock]]&lt;br /&gt;[[John Adams (died 1817)|John Adams]]}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Savile Finch]]&lt;br /&gt;[[John Dawnay, 4th Viscount Downe|The Viscount Downe]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Malton (UK Parliament constituency)|Member of Parliament for Malton]]|years=1774}}
{{s-aft|after= [[Savile Finch]]&lt;br /&gt;[[William Weddell]]}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Matthew Brickdale]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Robert Nugent, 1st Earl Nugent|The Viscount Clare PC]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Bristol (UK Parliament constituency)|Member of Parliament for Bristol]]|years=1774–1780}}
{{s-aft|after= [[Matthew Brickdale]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sir Henry Lippincott, 1st Baronet|Sir Henry Lippincott]]}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Savile Finch]]&lt;br /&gt;[[William Weddell]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Malton (UK Parliament constituency)|Member of Parliament for Malton]]|years=1780–1794}}
{{s-aft|after= [[George Damer, 2nd Earl of Dorchester|The Viscount Milton]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Richard Burke Jr.|Richard Burke]]}}
{{S-aca}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville|Henry Dundas]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Rector of the University of Glasgow]]|years=1783–1785}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Robert Cunninghame-Grahame of Gartmore]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{Edmund Burke}}
{{Age of Enlightenment}}
{{English historical school economists}}
{{French Revolution navbox}}
{{Conservatism footer}}
{{Authority control|VIAF=100173535|LCCN=n/79/040055}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
| NAME= Burke, Edmund
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
| SHORT DESCRIPTION=philosopher
| DATE OF BIRTH=12 July 1729
| PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Dublin]], Ireland
| DATE OF DEATH=9 July 1797
| PLACE OF DEATH=[[Beaconsfield]], England
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Burke, Edmund}}
[[Category:1729 births]]
[[Category:1797 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Dublin (city)]]
[[Category:Irish Anglicans]]
[[Category:Whig (British political party) MPs]]
[[Category:18th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:18th-century Irish writers]]
[[Category:18th-century British writers]]
[[Category:British people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:British political theorists]]
[[Category:Christian philosophers]]
[[Category:British classical liberals]]
[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:Early modern philosophers]]
[[Category:Historians of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:Irish diaspora politicians]]
[[Category:Members of the Parliament of Great Britain for English constituencies]]
[[Category:Members of the Privy Council of Great Britain]]
[[Category:Paymasters of the Forces]]
[[Category:People associated with Trinity College, Dublin]]
[[Category:Philosophers of art]]
[[Category:Political philosophers]]
[[Category:Politics of Bristol]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Rectors of the University of Glasgow]]
[[Category:Streathamites]]
[[Category:Articles which contain graphical timelines]]</text>
      <sha1>djcvvq83nw7b6ffkhfrzh4ye1dkfl6c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>