<http://dbpedia.org/resource/List_of_Atlas_Shrugged_characters> <http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract> "This is a list of characters in Ayn Rand's novel Atlas Shrugged."@en .
<http://dbpedia.org/resource/Animalia_(book)> <http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract> "Animalia is an illustrated children's book by Graeme Base. It was originally published in 1986, followed by a tenth anniversary edition in 1996 and a 25th anniversary edition in 2012. Over three million copies have been sold. A special numbered and signed anniversary edition was also published in 1996 with an embossed gold jacket."@en .
<http://dbpedia.org/resource/Alain_Connes> <http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract> "Alain Connes (French: [al\u025B\u0303 k\u0254n]; born 1 April 1947) is a French mathematician, currently Professor at the Coll\u00E8ge de France, IH\u00C9S, The Ohio State University and Vanderbilt University."@en .
<http://dbpedia.org/resource/International_Atomic_Time> <http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract> "International Atomic Time (TAI, from the French name Temps atomique international) is a high-precision atomic coordinate time standard based on the notional passage of proper time on Earth's geoid. It is the basis for Coordinated Universal Time (UTC), which is used for civil timekeeping all over the Earth's surface, and for Terrestrial Time, which is used for astronomical calculations. Since 30 June 2012 when the last leap second was added, TAI has been exactly 35 seconds ahead of UTC. The 35 seconds results from the initial difference of 10 seconds at the start of 1972, plus 25 leap seconds in UTC since 1972.Time coordinates on the TAI scales are conventionally specified using traditional means of specifying days, carried over from non-uniform time standards based on the rotation of the Earth. Specifically, both Julian Dates and the Gregorian calendar are used. TAI in this form was synchronised with Universal Time at the beginning of 1958, and the two have drifted apart ever since, due to the changing motion of the Earth."@en .
<http://dbpedia.org/resource/Allan_Dwan> <http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract> "Allan Dwan (3 April 1885 \u2013 28 December 1981) was a pioneering Canadian-born American motion picture director, producer and screenwriter."@en .
